<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/pisenberg/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.4.1" ident="GROBID" when="2016-09-09T13:40+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Describing Story Evolution from Dynamic Information Streams</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Stuart</forename>
								<surname>Rose</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Pacific Northwest National Laboratory</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Scott</forename>
								<surname>Butner</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Pacific Northwest National Laboratory</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Wendy</forename>
								<surname>Cowley</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Pacific Northwest National Laboratory</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Michelle</forename>
								<surname>Gregory</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Pacific Northwest National Laboratory</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName>
								<forename type="first">Julia</forename>
								<surname>Walker</surname>
							</persName>
							<affiliation>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Pacific Northwest National Laboratory</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Describing Story Evolution from Dynamic Information Streams</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Index Terms: H31 [Content Analysis and Indexing]: Abstracting methods—</term>
					<term>H33 [Information Search and Retrieval]: Information Filtering—</term>
					<term>H37 [Digital Libraries]: User Issues—</term>
					<term>I33 [Com- puter Graphics]: Picture/Image Generation—</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
				<p>Sources of streaming information, such as news syndicates, publish information continuously. Information portals and news aggrega-tors list the latest information from around the world enabling information consumers to easily identify events in the past 24 hours. The volume and velocity of these streams causes information from prior days to quickly vanish despite its utility in providing an informative context for interpreting new information. Few capabilities exist to support an individual attempting to identify or understand trends and changes from streaming information over time. The burden of retaining prior information and integrating with the new is left to the skills, determination, and discipline of each individual. In this paper we present a visual analytics system for linking essential content from information streams over time into dynamic stories that develop and change over multiple days. We describe particular challenges to the analysis of streaming information and present a fundamental visual representation for showing story change and evolution over time.</p>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">INTRODUCTION</head><p> Most information consumers interact with snapshots of an information space that is continually changing. Sources of information streams, such as news syndicates and information services, provide a variety of mechanisms for feeding the latest information by region , subject, or by user-defined search interests. However new information that arrives eclipses prior information. Although there are many interfaces for conveying the latest information, few if any capabilities provide a temporal context longer than 24 hours. Accurately identifying and intelligently describing change in an information space requires a context that relates new information with old. Fundamental tasks, such as tracking down initial precursors to an ongoing story can be problematic, particularly when stories span multiple documents and time intervals. Stories develop, merge, and split as they intersect and overlap with other stories over time. With a search interface to archived information, a user may formulate an effective query that recalls all documents related to a given story. However, identifying and exploring potential story connections using an archive search depends on each users prior knowledge of a related story and ability to formulate effective queries. Because it is human nature to prioritize and retain information that supports specific preferences, theories, or hypotheses, relying on individual abilities to acquire and maintain full coverage of a story's related context may actually diminish the objectivity and comprehensiveness of the coverage. We therefore consider the research presented here to provide a more effective means of discovering and maintaining coverage of information for a given analytic task as stories develop. This paper presents three contributions to the field of visual analytics that together enable computation and presentation of a lengthy temporal context in which new information can be situated with thematically related previous events. The first is a novel text analytic framework that extracts essential content from individual documents and computes significant themes occurring within documents collected into corpora or published within information streams. Applied to information streams, the analytic framework computes themes within time intervals enabling accurate detection of stories and their temporal dynamics. The second is a data model for describing and archiving the temporal context of significant themes in a manner that readily adapts to story changes and enables tracking of story evolution and dynamics. The third is a fundamental visual representation of story flow over time that conveys the temporal dynamics for all stories in an information space, enabling observation of story evolution, interaction, and flow over time. We consider the visual representation presented to be fundamental in nature, representing a basis for conveying the historic context and precursors to developing and ongoing stories. The data model presented exists independently of any visual representation and was developed to accomodate the dynamic nature of real stories. Stories are identifiable only as repeated joint membership of documents in the same sets. If documents do not repeatedly join up in the same set then they are not part of the same story. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">RELATED WORK</head><p> Our work relates to research on visual representations and analysis of structure and change in flows of information over time. Of particular interest is prior work related to temporal analysis of information which we explore in the next two sections. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Visual Methods</head><p>In his book, Envisioning Information, Tufte <ref type="bibr" coords="1,496.56,533.59,14.87,8.12">[15] </ref>describes a graphic time series produced in 1977 by Reebee Garofalo that tracks artistic genealogy and production among recording artists from 1955 to 1974. In Garofalo's graphic, names of recording artists are drawn on a two-dimensional cumulative trend plot, the horizontal axis representing time, the vertical axis generally representing market share. Artists are grouped by style of music and over time new artists are placed near those of similar styles. Tufte writes: Bearing some similarity to Garofalo's graphic, ThemeRiver <ref type="bibr" coords="1,318.00,713.83,9.68,8.12">[7,</ref><ref type="bibr" coords="1,330.24,713.83,7.43,8.12"> 6] </ref>provides a visual representation of the temporal rise and fall </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="99"></head><p>IEEE Symposium on Visual Analytics Science and Technology October 12 -13, Atlantic City, New Jersey, USA U.S. Government work not protected by U.S. copyright of major themes in a document corpus. While ThemeRiver automatically detects themes and their trends in order to show their temporal characteristics, individual items that constitute those trends are not visible, in contrast to the detailed labeling of artists in Garofalo's graphic. As a result ThemeRiver has a much lower information density. Although direct relationships between themes may exist in the corpus, they are not evident in ThemeRiver. Observation of the ThemeRiver visualization does not provide insight into how or to what extent themes interrelate. While correlation among themes may be inferred through observation of similar temporal patterns in ThemeRiver, direct influence between elements is not indicated. Representing the history of an individual document, HistoryFlow <ref type="bibr" coords="2,54.00,187.99,14.99,8.12">[17] </ref>presents a visualization of revision patterns made over the life of a document. The visualization mirrors the linear structure of the document, graphic representations of user revisions are shown in their location relative to the entire document and in the larger context of the document's history. The authors note the aid that the history flow visualization provides in understanding patterns of revisions and collaboration over time. Although focused on a single document, history flow effectively shows progression of all parts of a document in relation to each other. Themail <ref type="bibr" coords="2,99.00,278.35,14.87,8.12">[16] </ref>comprises a system for visualizing and exploring relationships based on interaction patterns as revealed through an individual's email archive. The authors note two distinct user interaction modes with the visualization, exploration of big picture trends and themes (haystack) and more detail-oriented exploration (needle). Based on user studies, the authors note that displaying large collections of keywords fostered user's insight into the evolution of relationships over time as users' past email exchanges were placed within a meaningful context. They also note that each users' familiarity with their respective email archives is essential in enabling efficient insight from the visualization. Single keywords in the visualization bring back memories of events and associated context . A user unfamiliar with the data would likely need to dig deeper into email content in order to resolve ambiguity associated with single keywords and to understand the context for particular keywords, relationships, and trends. A framework for tracking the popularity of quoted phrases (memes) through on-line text is described in <ref type="bibr" coords="2,226.80,448.39,13.70,8.12">[11]</ref>. The authors describe a framework for meme-tracking and demonstrate its utility in representing the news cycle and unique temporal patterns for news media and blogs. A stacked plot is presented for displaying the popularity of particular memes over time. A system for visualizing tags is described in <ref type="bibr" coords="2,233.28,498.79,9.51,8.12" target="#b2">[3]</ref>. The system characterizes the most interesting tags from an online image sharing community based on a sliding interval of time and provides an interactive visualization that allows the user to observe the temporal interestingness of tags as they evolve, at arbitrary scales in real time. Information about inter-relatedness of tags is not explored as the authors' focus is to show the latest, most interesting tags. A common characteristic across this related research is a focus on providing overview and generalization to a user through computational analysis and reduction of unstructured information to a set of specific features whose characteristics are conveyed in a high-level overview. Although HistoryFlow differs by focusing on a structured set of information, and representing changes to that structure, it effectively provides a high-level overview in which patterns of activity and dynamic changes are easily observed. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Analytic Methods</head><p>The analysis of unstructured information in order to select a set of representative features is critical, as features that are not detected can not be shown or measured. Previous research in the visual analytics and information retrieval community has focused on methods of selecting features through the application of corpus-oriented methods that rate candidate features according to their ability to statistically discriminate between sets of documents within the corpus. <ref type="bibr" coords="2,318.00,77.71,14.87,8.12">[13] </ref>and <ref type="bibr" coords="2,353.88,77.71,10.43,8.12">[9] </ref> describe positive results of selecting statistically discriminating words across a corpus to define an index vocabulary for the corpus. While these approaches are useful in many applications, features that are significant for individual documents may be lost by such corpus-oriented methods. In the context of time, stories that span a week may be overshadowed by major news trends that span a year. Because new features are likely to be less common than established features, corpus-oriented methods are likely to overlook features as they first appear. A set of features based on corpus-oriented methods must be reevaluated when the corpus changes. Because corpora based on information streams change frequently, this incurs significant performance hurdles with real information streams. Reprocessing the entirety of the corpus may also wipe out mental models that a user has developed to understand, explore, and explain an information space. Several of these challenges to analysis of streaming data were addressed in <ref type="bibr" coords="2,359.16,267.67,9.51,8.12">[8]</ref>. The authors describe a visual analytics system that enables analysis of dynamic corpora. The system provides multiple visual analytic tools for investigating the current state of a document corpus continually aging out old increments and adding new increments for analysis. The system avoids scalability issues by maintaining a sliding window over time, removing old documents as time moves onward. As this limits how far back in time a user can look, a feature is provided that allows a user to save a copy of any current increment of an analysis. A limitation of that system is that it only represents a single state, and provides no facilities for tracking changes across multiple time increments. The set of features for any increment are selected through corpus-oriented methods, relying on overlap across and gradual change between increments to transition the user across increments. As a result, if many increments pass between a user's last interactions with the system, they may spend significant time reorienting to the new information and any change in context. </p><p>To avoid the limitations of corpus-oriented methods of feature selection, we focus our interest on methods of keyword extraction that operate on individual documents. Such document-oriented methods extract the same keywords from a document regardless of the current state of a corpus. Document-oriented methods therefore provide context-independent document features and are suited to corpora that change As commonly defined in the recent literature, keywords may be single terms or comprise multiple words and phrases that reflect a document's content. Keywords provide a compact summary of a document and have been applied to improve many information retrieval (IR) systems, such as digital libraries, by linking documents via keywords, hyperlinks, citations, quotations, and key phrases. Themail <ref type="bibr" coords="2,364.32,580.75,14.99,8.12">[16] </ref> provides an example of such a system as it enables exploration of email archives through keywords due to their ability to trigger user associations to a larger context. Another system , Phrasier <ref type="bibr" coords="2,368.88,610.63,13.79,8.12">[10]</ref>, lists documents related to a primary document's keyphrases, and supports the use of keyphrase anchors as hyperlinks between documents, enabling a user to quickly access related material. Keyphind <ref type="bibr" coords="2,391.56,640.51,10.43,8.12" target="#b3">[4] </ref> uses keyphrases from documents as the basic building block for an IR system. As described in <ref type="bibr" coords="2,505.80,650.47,13.70,8.12">[14]</ref>, key ideas may also be extracted and used to augment a system for browsing digital libraries of books using key terms extracted from popularly quoted passages. Linking documents through essential content such as keywords enables exploration of associations between documents independent of a static and pre-defined corpus. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">ANALYTIC FRAMEWORK</head><p>Within this section we first define our method of feature selection, then we describe our method for computation and analysis of significant themes (CAST) and show application to a static document corpus for clarity, then describe how the analytic framework applies CAST to an information stream or dynamic corpus. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Feature Selection</head><p>Many text analysis techniques focus on what distinguishes a text from its encompassing document corpus. When the information is streaming, the corpus is dynamic and can change significantly over time. Techniques that evaluate documents by discriminating features are only valid for a snapshot in time. In order to eliminate the influence of a transient context or state in the larger information space we apply computational methods for characterizing each document individually. Such methods produce information on what a document is about, independent of its current context. Analyzing documents individually also further enables analysis of massive information streams as multiple documents can be analyzed in parallel or across a distributed architecture. In order to extract content that is readily identifiable by users, we apply the technology Rapid Automatic Keyword Extraction (RAKE) described in <ref type="bibr" coords="3,140.88,280.51,14.87,8.12">[12] </ref>to extract keywords from individual documents. RAKE takes a simple set of input parameters to extract keywords from a single document. <ref type="figure" coords="3,201.12,300.43,32.92,8.12">Figure 1</ref>shows extracted keywords as keywords of a news article from Voice of America. We consider keywords to include one or more words such as </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pakistan Muslim League-N leader Nawaz Sharif and criticized President Pervez Musharraf. </head><p>Keywords provide an advantage over other types of signatures as they are readily accessible to a user and can be easily applied to search other information spaces. The value of any particular keyword can be readily evaluated by a user for their particular interests and applied in multiple contexts. Furthermore, the direct correspondence of extracted keywords with the document text improves the accessibility of a user with the system. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Computation and Analysis of Significant Themes</head><p>For a given corpus, whether static or representing documents within an interval of time, the extracted keywords are grouped into coherent themes by applying a hierarchical agglomerative clustering algorithm to a keyword similarity matrix based on keyword document associations in the corpus. The association of each keyword to documents within the corpus is measured as the document's response to the keyword, which is obtained by submitting each keyword as a query to a Lucene index populated with documents from the corpus. The query response of each document hit greater than 0.1 is accumulated in the keyword's document response vector. Lucene calculates document similarity according to the vector space model described in <ref type="bibr" coords="3,230.64,549.79,13.79,8.12">[13]</ref>. We refer the reader to <ref type="bibr" coords="3,92.28,559.87,10.43,8.12" target="#b4">[5] </ref>for more complete implementation details. In most cases the number of document hits to a particular keyword query is a small subset of the total number of documents in the index. Keyword document response vectors typically have fewer entries than there are documents in the corpus and are very heterogenous. The similarity between each unique pair of keywords is calculated as the Sorensen similarity coefficient of the keywords' respective document response vectors. The Sorensen similarity coefficient <ref type="bibr" coords="3,54.00,639.55,14.87,8.12">[13] </ref>is used due to its effectiveness on heterogeneous vectors and is identical to 1.0 -Bray-Curtis distance <ref type="bibr" coords="3,191.16,649.51,13.70,8.12">[14]</ref>, shown in equation (1). </p><formula>BC ab = ∑ |a i − b i | ∑(ai + b i ) (1) </formula><p> Coherent groups of keywords can then be calculated by clustering keywords by their similarity. Because the number of coherent groups may be independent of the number of keywords extracted, <ref type="figure" coords="3,318.00,500.71,30.11,8.12">Figure 1</ref> : Sample document from Voice of America and its keywords extracted by RAKE. we apply Ward's hierarchical agglomerative clustering algorithm <ref type="bibr" coords="3,318.00,554.83,14.87,8.12">[18] </ref>which does not require a pre-defined number of clusters. Ward's hierarchical clustering begins by assigning each element to its own cluster and then successively joins the two most similar clusters into a new, higher-level, cluster until a single top level cluster is created from the two remaining, least similar, ones. The decision distance dd i j between these last two clusters is typically retained as the maximum decision distance dd max for the hierarchy and can be used to evaluate the coherence cc n of lower level clusters in the hierarchy as shown in equation (2). </p><formula>cc n = 1 − dd n dd max (2) </formula><p> Clusters that have greater internal similarity will have higher coherence . Using a high coherence threshold prevents CAST from selecting clusters that include broadly used keywords such as president that are likely to appear in multiple unrelated stories. Clusters  with a coherence threshold of 0.65 or greater are selected as candidate themes for the corpus. Each candidate theme comprises keywords that typically return the same set of documents when applied as a query. These keywords occur in multiple documents together and may intersect other stories singly or together. We select the final set of themes for the corpus by assigning documents to their most highly associated theme. After all documents in the corpus have been assigned, we filter out any candidate themes for which no documents have been assigned. Keywords within each theme are then ranked by their associations to documents assigned within the theme. Hence the top ranked keyword for each theme best represents documents assigned to the theme and is used as the theme's label. Before elaborating on how CAST is applied to multiple time intervals , we briefly show application of CAST to a static corpus. The following section presents results on application of RAKE and CAST to the Multi-Perspective Question Answering (MPQA) Cor- pus <ref type="bibr" coords="4,68.64,511.63,9.60,8.12" target="#b0">[1]</ref>The majority of the remaining themes computed by CAST have fewer than four documents assigned, an expected result given the random selection of the remainder of documents in the MPQA Cor- pus. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Describing Stories</head><p> We developed our analytic framework to operate on streaming information ; to extract essential content from documents as they are received and to calculate themes at defined time intervals. When the current time interval ends (one day in our evaluations), a set of keywords is selected from the extracted keywords and keyword document associations are measured for all documents published or received within the current and previous n intervals (n = 7 in our evaluations). Keywords are clustered into themes according to the similarity of their document associations, and each document occurring over the past n intervals is assigned to the theme for which it has the highest total response. The set of themes computed for the current interval are persisted along with their member keywords and document assignments . Overlap with previous and future themes may be evaluated against previous or future intervals by comparing overlap of keywords and document assignments. Themes that overlap with others across time together relate to the same story. Repeated co-occurrences of documents within themes across multiple intervals are meaningful as they indicate real similarity and relevance of content between those documents for those intervals. In addition to the expected addition of new documents to an existing story and aging out of documents older than n intervals, it is not uncommon for stories to gain or lose documents to other stories. Documents assigned to the same theme within one interval may be assigned to different themes in the next interval. This feature of how we develop and apply the data model to define themes at each interval enables our analytic framework to automatically adapt to future thematic changes and accommodates the reality that stories often intersect, split, and merge. In order to show its utility, we applied our analytic framework on documents within the TDT-2 corpus <ref type="bibr" coords="4,451.08,693.91,10.43,8.12" target="#b1">[2] </ref>tagged as originating from the Associated Press's (AP) World Stream program due to it's similarity to other news sources and information services of interest. <ref type="figure" coords="5,63.96,260.59,26.56,8.12" target="#tab_2">Table 2</ref> lists the CAST themes on January 12, 1998 for AP documents in the TDT-2 Corpus. The first column lists the count of documents assigned to each theme that were published before January 12. The second column lists each themes count of documents that were published on January 12. Comparing these counts across themes allows us to easily identify which stories are new for example chuan government, serena williams who is playing, men's match; which stories are the largest, for example hong kong and world swimming championships. In the following section, we describe two fundamental visual representations that provide greater insight into the characteristics of themes and stories over time. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">VISUAL REPRESENTATION</head><p>The analytic framework we have described analyzes documents within time intervals; generating for each time interval a set of themes, each theme comprising a coherent set of keywords from that interval's documents, and having assigned documents from the previous n intervals. We describe two visual representations that yield insight to the temporal context of documents, themes, and stories for an information consumer. The first view, a portion of which is shown in <ref type="figure" coords="5,227.04,474.07,25.18,8.12" target="#tab_3">Table 3</ref>, represents the current time interval and its themes. The view presents each theme as a listing of its member documents in ascending order by date. This view has the advantage of simplicity. An observer can easily assess the magnitude of each theme, its duration, and documents that have been added each day. However, lacking from this view is the larger temporal context and information on how related themes have changed and evolved over previous days. To provide a temporal context we developed the story flow visualization whose structure follows that of Garofalo's graphic mentioned previously and described in <ref type="bibr" coords="5,183.36,574.03,13.70,8.12">[15]</ref> . The story flow visualization , a portion of which is shown in <ref type="figure" coords="5,190.80,583.99,29.98,8.12" target="#fig_0">Figure 2</ref>, shows for a set of time intervals, the themes computed for those intervals, and their assigned documents which may link themes over time into stories. The visualization places days across the horizontal axis and orders daily themes along the vertical axis by their assigned document count. For a given interval, each theme is labeled with its top keyword in italics and lists its assigned documents in descending order by date. Each document is labeled with its title on the day that it is first published (or received), and rendered as a line connecting its positions across multiple days. This preserves space and reinforces the importance and time of each document, as the document title is only shown in one location. Similar lines across time intervals represent flows of documents assigned to the same themes, related Referring to <ref type="figure" coords="5,375.12,382.27,32.50,8.12" target="#fig_0">Figure 2</ref>, which is showing computed themes for four days of AP documents from the TDT-2 APW corpus, we can see that the top story for the first three days is initially labeled pakistan and india but changes to nuclear tests on the following two days. The theme pakistan and india loses two documents to other themes on the following day. These are likely documents that do not relate directly to the theme nuclear tests and therefore were assigned to other stories as the earlier theme pakistan and india became more focused on nuclear tests. No documents published on June 2 are assigned to the nuclear tests theme. Another story that is moving up over the days begins as ethnic albanians and quickly becomes labeled as kosovo. Stories can skip days, as shown by the documents related to the broader tokyo stock price index themes that appear on June 2 and June 4. </p><p> Ordering schemes that take into account relative positions of related groups across days may minimize line crossings at interval boundaries. However we have chosen to consistently order themes for each interval by their number of assigned documents so that the theme order for each day is unaffected by future days. This preserves the organization of themes in the story flow visualization across days and supports information consumers' extended interaction over days and weeks. An individual or team would therefore be able to print out each day's story flow column with document titles and lines, and post that next to the previous day's columns. Such an approach would be unrestricted by monitor resolution and support interaction and collaboration through manual edits and notes on the paper hard copies. Each foot of wall space could hold up to seven daily columns, enabling a nine foot wall to hold two months worth of temporal context along a single horizontal span. </p><p> On a single high-resolution monitor, seven days are easily rendered as each daily column is allocated 300 pixels which accomodates most document titles. Longer time periods can be made accessible through the application of a scrolling function. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>06</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>lebanon broader tokyo stock price index </head><p>Dollar edges lower, stocks fall in Tokyo trading </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>child labor </head><p>Child marchers breathe new life into old U.N. agency </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>israeli prime minister benjamin netanyahu </head><p>Saudi prince holds more talks on summit, Jordan wants moderate </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>leader suharto </head><p>Indonesia</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">DISCUSSION</head><p> The following discussion explores the described analytic framework and story flow visualization on AP documents within the TDT-2 Corpus. For cases in which multiple documents with identical titles occurred on the same day, we included only the latest version within the analysis. The 10,671 analyzed AP documents span a 6 month period from January 4, 1998 to June 30, 1998. The AP documents span a range of subjects and primarily cover international topics. Major stories include the olympics, the world cup, iraq, kosovo, human rights, nuclear tests, and many others. <ref type="figure" coords="6,63.96,390.67,31.96,8.12">Figure 3</ref>shows the story flow visualization on four weeks of AP documents. At a macro level, it can be observed that a few stories dominate the first two weeks presented in <ref type="figure" coords="6,206.16,410.59,35.29,8.12">Figure 3a</ref>. On <ref type="bibr" coords="6,261.72,410.59,32.32,8.12;6,54.00,420.55,29.92,8.12">February 28, 1998</ref>, the top story essentially ends and only small themes are visible until March 5, 1998, in <ref type="figure" coords="6,167.88,430.51,37.72,8.12">Figure 3b</ref>when a new story starts to accumulate new documents. Over the next seven days, that story adds approximately 40 new documents. The motivated reader is encouraged to acquire an electronic version of this paper and zoom into <ref type="figure" coords="6,69.72,470.35,31.36,8.12">Figure 3</ref>at 500%. At this scale, the individual theme labels and document titles can be easily read and story dynamics observed. <ref type="figure" coords="6,63.96,491.71,32.92,8.12">Figure 4</ref>shows the story flow visualization on one week of AP documents. The main stories include world cup, kosovo, eu, english fans, and japanese yen. On June 15, kosovo and nato are separate stories that later merge on June 17. On June 20 the story is relabeled as kosovo albanians suggesting a new development. Also on June 20, the world cup game story splits out across multiple themes, iran, world cup finals, korea's choi yong-soo, players only to rejoin again on June 21. This is likely due to an increase in the number of documents published on June 20 that individually relate to specific sub-themes of world cup game such as specific countries and players. While story evolution for large stories is easy to identify, single articles and stories that last two to three days are more difficult to spot. This is not unexpected, as the story flow visualization is designed to show story evolution over time and gives priority to the larger themes in the layout. Themes that do not develop into stories are not optimally represented and would likely benefit from a selective filtering operation or a second visualization in which the main stories play a less dominant role. Anecdotal feedback from potential users suggest that a filtering mechanism would be welcome in order to minimize line crossings and enable investigation into specific stories and themes. It was also suggested that in application, the story flow visualization would likely be focused on a specific subject area, although the high-level overview was considered effective for users that only need to understand the major story dynamics. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">CONCLUSIONS AND FUTURE WORK</head><p>We have described a novel analytic framework for automatically computing themes and tracking stories as they develop over time and have presented a fundamental visual representation upon which user interface designers can iterate interaction refinements for specific applications. We anticipate that systems applying these methods will enable information consumers to more effectively integrate new information and understand developments over time. Future work to build on the visual representation presented here will likely focus on identifying preferred interaction and selection capabilities to support information consumers' work flows. In this paper we presented contributions to the field of visual analytics ; a novel analytic framework for calculating themes based on automatically extracted keywords and documents from information streams, a data model that captures requisite temporal information for tracking and adapting to evolving stories, and a visual representation of story flow that conveys temporal context for an information space, enabling information consumers to rapidly identify change and investigate story evolution over time. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>02</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>power supply company mercury energy </head><p>Power company concedes it may be at fault for city blackout. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>israeli prime minister benjamin netanyahu </head><p>Israel, Palestinians make progress on Palestinian airport </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>sunni muslim group </head><p>Three people killed in bloody gun battle Pakistan police arrest eight men in wake of religious attacks </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>gold medals </head><p>Four−time gold medalist dismayed at track and field today </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>chang nokia employs 36,600 people </head><p>Retransmitting to restore slugline. title </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>illegal logging scandal </head><p>Burmese refugees given one week to relocate or face Some royals reportedly wary of change </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ethiopian−born saudi financier sheikh mohamed hussein al amoudi </head><p>African leaders, businessmen promote investment in continent </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>romanian 5,000−meter world champion ran </head><p>Szabo sets 2,000 mark, two women break pole vault mark Szabo breaks women's indoor 2,000 indoor mark </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>kurdish rebel group pkk </head><p>Police break up pro−Kurdish demonstration in </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>english fans </head><p>Marseille, Paris, Toulouse prepare security for matches Marseille gets set for second World Cup weekend </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>russian president boris yeltsin </head><p>Chubais back, says Russia needs dlrs 10 billion to 15 billion in </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>democratic party </head><p>Elections official says St. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Vincent and the Grenadines vote was </head><p>Poll shows solid support for major 'agreement' parties in N. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>detroit red wings south african president nelson mandela </head><p>Pope receives Mandela in Vatican </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>eritrean rebels au pair louise woodward arrived </head><p>Britain gives muted welcome mixed with digust to au pair's return </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>interfax news agency </head><p>Washington has no immediate solution for Ukraine's Turboatom </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>nba players </head><p>NBA to consider moratorium in labor dispute </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>west bank </head><p>Netanyahu: Israel is considering referendum on West Bank pullback </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>prominent political prisoners financial times−stock exchange 100−share index </head><p>London share prices lower at midday </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>au pair louise woodward arrived </head><p>Residents in Louise Woodward's hometown giving her breathing space </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>mandela stewart </head><p>Stewart stumbles but holds one−stroke lead at U.S. Open Stewart dances to first−round lead at Open </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>interfax news agency quoted chubais diplomatic compound </head><p>Belarus cuts water and power to ambassadors' residence </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>south african captain lucas radebe </head><p>Danes in shock after referee expels three from World Cup match vs. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>cart </head><p>Casey Martin rides into weekend play despite some poor driving </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>gambian foreign minister mohamed sedat jobe </head><p>Artillery </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0" coords="6,144.00,249.43,323.96,8.12"><head>Figure 2: </head><figDesc>Figure 2: Story flow visualization on four low volume days from the TDT-2 APW Corpus. </figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1" validated="true" coords="4,54.00,54.79,504.02,241.67"><figDesc coords="4,54.00,54.79,504.02,8.12;4,54.00,64.75,241.16,8.12">Table 1: MPQA Topics and CAST Themes. Each row contains the defined topic and description within the Defined Topics column and the labeled theme and top keywords within the CAST Themes column.</figDesc><table coords="4,60.00,96.04,494.19,200.42">Defined Topics 
CAST Themes 
mugabe 
mugabe's re-election (46) 
2002 presidental election in Zimbabwe 
zimbabwe's election, mugabe, mugabe's, president mugabe, mugabe's government 
guantanamo 
guantanamo prisoners (43) 
U.S. holding prisoners in Guantanamo Bay 
detainees as prisoners, detainees prisoners, prisoners of war, war prisoners, prisoners 
kyoto 
kyoto protocol on climate (40) 
ratification of Kyoto Protocol 
kyoto protocol, ratification of the kyoto protocol, 1997 kyoto protocol 
venezuela 
venezuela's president hugo chavez (37) 
presidential coup in Venezuela 
venezuelan president hugo chavez, president hugo chavez, president chavez, hugo chavez 
settlements 
israeli (34) 
Israeli settlements in Gaza and West Bank 
palestinian, israel, occupied palestinian, israeli occupation, palestinian people's 
taiwan 
china under which taiwan (31) 
relations between Taiwan and China 
taiwan, united states and taiwan, taiwan issue, taiwan policy, taiwan affairs, taiwan strait 
axisofevil 
axis of evil (28) 
reaction to President Bush's 2002 State of the Union Address 
north korea as axis, iran and north korea, iran or north korea, iraq and north korea, 
humanrights 
human rights (28) 
reaction to U.S. State Department report on human rights 
human rights report, annual human rights report, human rights violations, rights 
spacestation 
space station (28) 
space missions of various countries 
international space station, space, international space, space shuttle, russian space mission 
argentina 
argentina (12) 
economic collapse in Argentina 
argentina's, help argentina, argentine government, argentine, worried argentina 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2" validated="false" coords="4,54.00,511.63,240.13,210.24"><figDesc coords="4,78.24,511.63,3.20,8.12;4,54.00,529.40,176.08,8.60;4,54.00,543.43,240.02,8.12;4,54.00,553.39,239.99,8.12;4,54.00,563.35,240.02,8.12;4,54.00,573.31,239.90,8.12;4,54.00,583.27,68.12,8.12;4,63.96,593.47,230.01,8.12;4,54.00,603.43,239.77,8.12;4,54.00,613.39,240.04,8.12;4,54.00,623.35,239.87,8.12;4,54.00,633.31,240.04,8.12;4,54.00,643.27,239.96,8.12;4,54.00,653.23,240.13,8.12;4,54.00,663.19,181.05,8.12">. 3.2.1 CAST Themes for the MPQA Corpus The MPQA Corpus consists of 535 news articles provided by the Center for the Extraction and Summarization of Events and Opinions in Text (CERATOPS). Articles in the MPQA Corpus are from 187 different foreign and U.S. news sources and date from June 2001 to May 2002. We applied RAKE to extract keywords from the title and text fields of documents in the MPQA Corpus and selected keywords from those extracted that occured in at least 2 documents. We then applied CAST to compute themes for the corpus. Of the 535 documents in the MPQA Corpus 327 were assigned to 10 themes which align with the 10 defined topics for the corpus as shown in Table 1. The number of documents that CAST assigned to each theme is shown in parentheses. As defined by CERATOPS:</figDesc><table coords="4,73.92,684.00,200.15,37.88">The majority of the articles are on 10 different topics, 
but a number of additional articles were randomly se-
lected (more or less) from a larger corpus of 270,000 
documents. 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3" validated="true" coords="5,54.96,54.79,237.97,170.39"><figDesc coords="5,54.96,54.79,237.97,8.12">Table 2: CAST Themes for 01/12/1998 and their document counts</figDesc><table coords="5,71.64,85.00,204.63,140.18">Assigned Docs 
&lt; 01/12 
01/12 
Theme 
1 
5 
chuan government 
0 
3 
serena williams who is playing 
0 
3 
men's match 
0 
2 
stabilizing japan's shaken financial system 
0 
1 
women's race 
1 
2 
news agency 
3 
2 
five-kilometer race 
3 
1 
northern ireland 
5 
1 
japanese prime minister ryutaro hashimoto 
6 
1 
world cup 
7 
1 
president suharto 
9 
3 
world swimming championships 
15 
4 
hong kong 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4" validated="true" coords="5,318.00,54.79,239.96,319.16"><figDesc coords="5,318.00,54.79,239.80,8.12">Table 3: Documents Assigned to CAST Theme iraq on 02/14/1998</figDesc><table coords="5,318.00,84.65,239.96,289.30">Day 
Document Title 
02-07 
U.N. to excavate weapons dumps in Iraq 
02-07 
Kuwaiti government to distribute gas masks in two days 
02-07 
U.N. to excavate dumps where chemical weapons and warheads buried 
02-08 
Saudi Arabia will not back military strike against Iraq 
02-08 
Egyptian Foreign Minister upbeat on diplomatic end to US-Iraq 
02-08 
Russian FM: Dispute over Iraq has not damaged U.S.-Russian 
02-08 
U.S. won't ask Saudis to allow attacks from their territory 
02-08 
Iraq says talks on weapons destruction making progress 
02-09 
Citing regional tensions, Annan cancels visit to the Middle East 
02-09 
Canada: No decision yet on commitment against Iraq 
02-09 
byline 
02-09 
control on Yeltsin-Annan remarks, other new material 
02-09 
Iraq launches campaign to rally Arab support 
02-09 
Iraq crisis at 'critical stage,' U.N. chief pushes for peaceful 
02-10 
Report: Lebanon tells Iraq to cooperate with weapons inspectors 
02-10 
Iraqi foreign minister seeks Syrian support in standoff 
02-10 
Precede MAJDAL SHAMS 
02-10 
Iraqi ambassador says Baghdad cannot meet Annan's proposed sales 
02-10 
Israel short on gas masks for children 
02-11 
Iraqi daily says Washington always determined to use force 
02-11 
Britain rejects latest Iraqi offer on weapons 
02-11 
Iraq puts oil export potential at 1.6 million barrels daily 
02-11 
Gulf foreign ministers meet to discuss unified stand on Iraq 
02-11 
BC-Iraq-Opposition 
02-11 
Santer says EU position will change if Iraq stays defiant 
02-12 
Iraqi foreign minister calls U.S. rejection 'a bluff' 
02-12 
UN advises vacationing staff to stay away from Iraq 
02-13 
American, Russian defense chiefs hold cordial talks at military 
02-13 
Iraq accuses U.S. of psychological warfare 
02-13 
U.S. envoy meets with Japanese leaders on Iraq 
02-13 
Foreign Office urges 'higher degree of caution' for travelers 
02-13 
Iraq dispute underlines strain in U.S.-Russia ties 
02-14 
U.S. envoy seeks China's support on Iraq 
02-14 
Demonstrators at U.S. Embassy in Japan urge no military attack 
02-14 
Iraq urges diplomacy, releases Egyptian prisoners 

to the same story. As stories grow over days, they add more lines. 
A document's line ends when it is no longer associated with any 
themes. 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5" validated="false" coords="6,54.23,53.77,446.78,80.68"><figDesc coords="6,86.72,53.77,36.73,10.71;6,203.39,53.77,45.91,10.71;6,329.25,53.77,45.91,10.71;6,455.10,53.77,45.91,10.71;6,54.23,70.85,41.33,4.87;6,55.30,76.76,102.84,4.46;6,54.23,91.36,18.24,4.87;6,54.23,102.08,34.49,4.87;6,55.30,107.99,81.38,4.46;6,55.30,113.12,79.68,4.46;6,54.23,121.19,21.94,4.87;6,54.23,129.58,74.94,4.87;6,180.09,70.85,29.07,4.87;6,180.09,84.83,16.24,4.87;6,181.15,90.74,111.12,4.46;6,181.15,95.87,93.06,4.46">/01/1998 06/02/1998 06/03/1998 06/04/1998 pakistan and india India denies it plans another nuclear test, urges nuclear talks lebanon ethnic albanian More deaths reported in Kosovo; thousands flee More deaths reported in Kosovo; hundreds flee world cup nicole mott's penalty corner drive nuclear tests kosovo Fleeing ethnic Albanians describe destruction from Serb offensive Romania and Macedonia ask for U.S. troops in Kosovo</figDesc><table></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6" validated="false" coords="6,180.09,70.85,366.22,109.28"><figDesc coords="6,307.01,121.98,100.50,4.46;6,305.94,127.10,5.95,4.46;6,305.94,132.85,44.03,4.87;6,307.01,138.76,89.66,4.46;6,431.80,70.85,16.24,4.87;6,431.80,80.17,70.96,4.87;6,432.86,86.08,67.12,4.46;6,431.80,93.69,23.37,4.87;6,431.80,102.08,33.91,4.87;6,432.86,107.99,108.76,4.46;6,431.80,114.67,51.29,4.87;6,432.86,120.58,113.45,4.46">Imported autos sales in Japan down for 14th straight month title high−speed rail link Britain gets new deal to speed Channel Tunnel trains kosovo broader tokyo stock price index Dollar rises, stocks slip in Tokyo trading child labor water shortage New Zealand claims world first of extracting pure water from thin dejammet urged butler U.N. inspectors challenge Baghdad's claims it has destroyed illegal</figDesc><table coords="6,180.09,70.85,336.35,109.28">'s new leader unconcerned about past corruption 

nicole mott's penalty corner drive 

world cup 

nuclear tests 

U.S. ambassador: nuclear proliferation not only U.S. problem 

kosovo 

child labor 

penalty corner 

imported trucks plunged 47.9 percent 

imported trucks plunged 47.9 percent 
high−speed rail link 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7" validated="false" coords="7,56.68,56.34,490.39,184.32"><figDesc coords="7,541.79,56.34,5.28,3.08;7,56.68,61.25,33.67,2.98;7,56.99,64.42,24.44,1.28;7,56.99,65.90,26.21,1.28;7,56.68,71.03,12.62,1.40;7,56.99,72.73,27.73,1.28;7,56.68,77.20,12.13,1.40;7,56.99,78.90,24.31,1.28;7,56.99,80.38,9.07,1.28;7,56.68,83.23,32.74,1.40;7,56.99,84.93,27.24,1.28;7,56.99,86.41,21.69,1.28;7,56.99,87.88,23.64,1.28;7,56.68,90.47,6.31,1.40;7,56.99,92.17,28.47,1.28;7,56.99,93.65,12.71,1.28;7,56.68,96.23,7.70,1.40;7,56.99,97.93,31.44,1.28;7,56.99,99.41,31.10,1.28;7,56.68,101.87,19.79,1.40;7,56.68,104.68,8.60,1.40;7,56.99,106.38,28.83,1.28;7,56.99,107.85,28.47,1.28;7,56.99,109.33,26.21,1.28;7,56.68,111.38,26.88,1.40;7,56.68,114.06,23.11,1.40;7,56.68,116.74,20.41,1.40;7,56.99,118.44,27.92,1.28;7,56.68,120.77,7.62,1.40;7,56.99,122.46,22.06,1.28;7,56.99,123.94,17.11,1.28;7,56.99,125.41,22.67,1.28;7,56.68,127.33,9.92,1.40;7,56.68,129.88,18.19,1.40;7,56.99,131.58,30.06,1.28;7,92.87,61.25,25.66,2.98;7,93.18,64.42,25.84,1.28;7,93.18,65.90,26.33,1.28;7,93.18,67.37,21.50,1.28;7,93.18,68.85,24.13,1.28;7,93.18,70.32,21.14,1.28;7,93.18,71.80,19.61,1.28;7,92.87,78.00,12.62,1.40;7,93.18,79.71,18.76,2.76;7,92.87,86.05,27.20,1.40;7,93.18,87.75,32.51,1.28;7,93.18,89.22,26.76,1.28;7,92.87,92.48,12.13,1.40;7,92.87,95.70,19.79,1.40;7,93.18,97.40,24.56,1.28;7,92.87,99.99,9.92,1.40;7,93.18,101.69,19.06,1.28;7,93.18,103.16,27.74,1.28;7,92.87,105.48,20.00,1.40;7,93.18,107.18,32.35,1.28;7,93.18,108.66,22.42,1.28;7,92.87,110.98,7.70,1.40;7,93.18,112.68,27.86,1.28;7,93.18,114.15,27.95,1.28;7,92.87,116.21,18.19,1.40;7,93.18,117.91,32.62,1.28;7,92.87,120.09,26.88,1.40;7,92.87,122.64,5.49,1.40;7,93.18,124.34,28.78,1.28;7,129.06,61.25,31.07,2.98;7,129.37,64.42,29.76,1.28;7,129.37,65.90,30.73,1.28;7,129.37,67.37,28.11,1.28;7,129.37,68.85,32.99,1.28;7,129.06,74.52,12.62,1.40;7,129.37,76.22,9.07,1.28;7,129.06,81.36,13.44,1.40;7,129.37,83.06,17.11,1.28;7,129.37,84.53,32.56,1.28;7,129.37,86.01,27.55,1.28;7,129.06,88.59,8.03,1.40;7,129.37,90.29,24.13,1.28;7,129.37,91.77,30.55,1.28;7,129.06,94.49,12.13,1.40;7,129.06,97.71,27.20,1.40;7,129.06,100.93,29.54,1.40;7,129.06,103.88,20.24,1.40;7,129.37,105.58,27.22,1.28;7,129.06,108.03,21.08,2.98;7,129.06,112.19,16.56,1.40;7,129.37,113.89,29.75,1.28;7,129.37,115.36,24.41,1.28;7,129.37,116.83,27.71,1.28;7,129.06,118.89,7.70,1.40;7,129.37,120.59,34.46,1.28;7,129.06,122.91,5.49,1.40;7,129.37,124.61,31.90,1.28;7,165.56,62.95,30.79,2.76;7,165.56,65.90,17.84,1.28;7,165.56,67.37,9.07,1.28;7,165.56,68.85,7.70,1.28;7,165.56,70.32,9.07,1.28;7,165.56,71.80,30.48,1.28;7,165.26,75.99,31.22,2.98;7,165.56,79.17,30.79,1.28;7,165.56,80.64,26.46,1.28;7,165.26,84.57,20.41,1.40;7,165.56,86.27,27.92,1.28;7,165.26,89.80,7.95,1.40;7,165.56,91.50,28.29,1.28;7,165.56,92.98,24.81,1.28;7,165.26,95.56,12.13,1.40;7,165.26,98.65,15.41,1.40;7,165.56,100.35,24.55,1.28;7,165.56,101.82,9.07,1.28;7,165.56,103.30,12.22,1.28;7,165.26,105.62,5.25,1.40;7,165.56,107.32,32.93,1.28;7,165.56,108.79,16.80,1.28;7,165.56,110.27,32.90,1.28;7,165.26,112.59,29.54,1.40;7,165.26,115.54,7.70,1.40;7,165.56,117.24,32.93,1.28;7,165.26,119.69,13.44,1.40;7,165.26,122.51,14.26,1.40;7,165.26,125.32,20.49,1.40;7,165.56,127.02,22.82,1.28;7,165.26,129.48,19.26,1.40;7,165.56,131.18,33.79,1.28;7,165.56,132.65,29.48,1.28;7,165.26,134.84,29.45,2.98;7,165.26,138.86,14.18,1.40;7,165.56,140.56,32.68,1.28;7,201.45,61.25,28.62,2.98;7,201.75,64.42,19.55,1.28;7,201.75,65.90,12.95,1.28;7,201.75,67.37,19.55,1.28;7,201.45,73.31,12.62,1.40;7,201.75,75.01,9.07,1.28;7,201.75,76.49,10.87,1.28;7,201.75,77.96,21.26,1.28;7,201.75,79.44,29.54,1.28;7,201.75,80.91,30.00,1.28;7,201.75,82.39,9.07,1.28;7,201.75,83.86,32.66,1.28;7,201.75,85.33,23.83,1.28;7,201.75,86.81,5.25,1.28;7,201.45,91.68,15.41,1.40;7,201.75,93.38,21.63,1.28;7,201.45,96.23,16.72,1.40;7,201.75,97.93,28.17,1.28;7,201.75,99.41,30.79,1.28;7,201.45,102.13,7.95,1.40;7,201.75,103.83,30.61,1.28;7,201.75,105.31,32.93,1.28;7,201.45,108.03,20.53,1.40;7,201.75,109.73,24.19,1.28;7,201.75,111.21,20.59,1.28;7,201.45,113.79,20.49,1.40;7,201.45,116.61,7.70,1.40;7,201.45,119.29,13.44,1.40;7,201.75,120.99,26.97,1.28;7,201.75,122.46,30.24,1.28;7,201.45,124.65,19.26,1.40;7,201.75,126.35,23.73,1.28;7,201.45,128.67,8.85,1.40;7,201.75,130.37,26.02,1.28;7,201.75,131.85,29.57,1.28;7,237.64,61.25,17.96,2.98;7,237.94,64.42,28.22,1.28;7,237.94,65.90,26.18,1.28;7,237.94,67.37,28.92,1.28;7,237.94,68.85,29.54,1.28;7,237.94,70.32,27.55,1.28;7,237.94,71.80,29.72,1.28;7,237.94,73.27,30.85,1.28;7,237.94,74.75,30.42,1.28;7,237.64,81.62,12.62,1.40;7,237.94,83.32,9.07,1.28;7,237.94,84.80,28.08,1.28;7,237.94,86.27,32.25,1.28;7,237.94,87.75,5.25,1.28;7,237.64,93.02,7.95,1.40;7,237.94,94.72,27.55,1.28;7,237.64,97.84,15.41,1.40;7,237.94,99.54,29.08,1.28;7,237.94,101.02,20.59,1.28;7,237.64,103.88,19.18,1.40;7,237.94,105.58,31.28,1.28;7,237.94,107.05,26.27,1.28;7,237.64,109.91,7.13,1.40;7,237.94,111.61,30.24,1.28;7,273.83,61.25,23.10,2.98;7,274.14,64.42,20.53,1.28;7,274.14,65.90,4.40,1.28;7,274.14,67.37,29.17,1.28;7,273.83,73.31,12.62,1.40;7,274.14,75.01,23.95,1.28;7,274.14,76.49,11.91,1.28;7,274.14,77.96,25.23,1.28;7,273.83,83.63,19.06,1.40;7,274.14,85.33,25.48,1.28;7,274.14,86.81,26.21,1.28;7,274.14,88.28,28.23,1.28;7,273.83,91.68,19.18,1.40;7,273.83,95.03,15.41,1.40;7,273.83,98.25,16.72,1.40;7,274.14,99.95,29.38,1.28;7,273.83,102.80,7.95,1.40;7,274.14,104.50,25.72,1.28;7,273.83,107.36,7.13,1.40;7,273.83,110.31,7.70,1.40;7,274.14,112.01,23.64,1.28;7,273.83,114.47,20.49,1.40;7,274.14,116.16,21.87,1.28;7,274.14,117.64,28.96,1.28;7,274.14,192.70,27.01,1.28;7,273.83,194.35,26.27,2.98;7,273.83,197.71,20.41,1.40;7,310.02,61.25,19.06,1.40;7,310.33,62.95,30.00,1.28;7,310.33,64.42,26.58,1.28;7,310.33,65.90,27.86,1.28;7,310.33,67.37,30.22,1.28;7,310.33,95.39,22.73,1.28;7,310.33,96.86,15.58,1.28;7,310.33,98.34,27.80,1.28;7,310.02,101.73,20.41,1.40;7,310.33,103.43,27.98,1.28;7,310.33,104.91,25.90,1.28;7,310.33,106.38,21.99,1.28;7,310.02,109.77,16.72,1.40;7,310.33,111.47,27.95,1.28;7,310.02,114.20,6.39,1.40;7,310.33,115.90,28.19,1.28;7,310.02,118.62,7.87,1.40;7,310.02,121.44,30.85,2.98;7,310.02,125.32,29.99,1.40;7,310.33,127.02,22.67,1.28;7,346.52,62.95,28.47,1.28;7,346.52,64.42,21.32,1.28;7,346.52,65.90,22.97,1.28;7,346.52,67.37,28.84,1.28;7,346.52,68.85,24.93,1.28;7,346.52,70.32,28.83,1.28;7,346.52,71.80,24.80,1.28;7,346.52,73.27,26.33,1.28;7,346.52,74.75,24.99,1.28;7,346.52,76.22,25.05,1.28;7,346.52,77.69,31.34,1.28;7,346.52,79.17,31.53,1.28;7,346.21,88.46,11.06,1.40;7,346.21,93.69,5.25,1.40;7,346.52,95.39,26.76,1.28;7,346.21,98.25,7.70,1.40;7,346.52,99.95,25.72,1.28;7,346.21,102.80,25.24,1.40;7,346.52,104.50,24.68,1.28;7,346.21,107.23,13.68,1.40;7,346.21,110.04,20.49,1.40;7,346.21,112.86,29.99,3.95;7,346.21,117.82,5.49,1.40;7,346.52,119.52,24.32,1.28;7,346.21,121.57,8.85,1.40;7,346.52,123.27,23.70,1.28">1998 iraq Iraq warns Kuwait to keep Americans out, vow to defend presidential Jordan determined to seal border to Iraqi refugees Chinese president worried about escalating Gulf crisis olympic gold medal Chinese skier leading women's aerials after preliminaries combined downhill Seizinger wins two downhill races; Wiberg second Ld−Writethru,0279 iraqi foreign minister mohammed saeed al−sahhaf Swedish minister 'pessimistic' over solution to Iraq crisis Iraqi, Kuwaiti envoys hold talks on Gulf crisis Iraqi foreign minister to meet with Chirac in Paris world cup Rangers say PSV's Advocaat is new coach; Gullit to PSV? U.S. aerialist injured in fall south korea South Korea's president−elect denies meeting Taiwanese leader Experts: North Korea appears to be easing stance toward Seoul nigerian−led intervention force armed forces Former top military official suspected of corruption released New military chief installed as riots flare again in Indonesia New military chief installed as troops watch for trouble georgian president eduard shevardnadze yasser arafat's palestinian authority iraqi president saddam hussein American troops conduct drills in Kuwait near Iraqi border south africa Johnstone holds on for victory in Dunhill PGA Johnstone wins South African PGA Fraud trial of disgraced ANC leader postponed harada needed foreign secretary robin cook Britain promises new campaign to lift Rushdie death sentence iraq Bahrain refuses U.S. access to bases for Iraq attack Yeltsin: Russia insists that Iraq meet U.N. resolutions U.N. makes plans, Kurds abandon northern Iraq camp Mubarak meets with Greek defense minister Hamas leaflet threatens attack if U.S. attacks Iraq Iraq blasts U.S. for interfering in Annan visit Report: Israel told Iraq it won't strike first olympic gold medal BULLETIN Gianni wins gold, another world record israeli prime minister benjamin netanyahu U.S. expected to announce Mideast peace ideas despite Iraq crisis Thousands of Palestinians still under Israeli occupation combined downhill nigerian−led intervention force Ecomog troops to extend control outside Freetown harada needed Japanese crowd cheers team to victory Japan clinches gold after record leaps by Okabe, Harada chinese news agency reported Tough−talking former general declares candidacy for governorship Authorities close 14,700 illegal mines in China south korea German finance minister praises South Korea for reforms Korean−American radio journalist fined dlrs 2,000 for libel foreign secretary robin cook Cook says Security Council very close to agreement on Annan Trip georgian president eduard shevardnadze sinn fein Sinn Fein faces banishment as others warn of IRA violence iraq Palestinian police arrest pro−Iraq demonstrators; new rally held In Romania, Italian president states opposition U.S. attack on Malaysia opposes military strikes against Iraq, urges diplomacy Iraqi opposition says ready to participate in change in Iraq Russia welcomes U.N. secretary general's planned visit to Baghdad olympic gold medal Ld−Writethru,0709 human rights groups Saudi beheaded for murdering wife Chiapas draws international attention as Mexican government calls Chinese dissidents demand political reforms, free unions central bank Devaluation fails to spark foreign currency market Indonesia still planning for currency board, bank governor says combined downhill israeli prime minister benjamin netanyahu foreign minister mohammed saeed al−sahhaf olympic ice hockey tournament Finland eliminates defending gold medalist Sweden 2−1 jump Two U.Stone, Bergoust sweep aerials gold 97 percent bosnian serbs Western Bosnian town symbolic of NATO's thorniest problem U.N. investigates arson cases in Croat−held Drvar U.N. investigate arson cases in Croat−held town of Drvar south korea U.S. Commerce Secretary: Asia must change the way it does business sinn fein Sinn Fein leaders hope judge can defend their seat in peace talks BULLETIN Head of North American league says ouster of Americans not a Finland a surprise entry in semifinals Ld−Writethru,0564 With AP Photos Ld−Writethru,0363 Germany wins women's biathlon relay against archrival Russia iraq Blast damages American car dealership; Iraq protest suspected Palestinian backlash could prove greater threat than Iraq attack U.N. reducing staff in Iraq as precaution against attack iraqi president saddam hussein U.N. relief workers start leaving as Iraq readies for Annan hong kong's Asian markets mostly rise with steep gains in South Korea Billionaire Li Ka−shing to leave blue−chip company combined downhill slalom and giant slalom Gerg surprises field with victory in women's slalom Ld−Writethru,0228 SHIGA KOGEN: in 1980. hun sen Cambodian resistance general looking for remains of missing Briton King to return to Cambodia in April Cambodian co−premier says fast admission into ASEAN will benefit foreign minister mohammed saeed al−sahhaf south korea South Korea's Samsung to sell heavy equipment business to Volvo, human rights groups central bank governor palestinian leader yasser arafat Police fire in the air to disperse pro−Iraq march president−elect kim dae−jung Report: South Korean agents responsible for 1973 kidnapping of then Report: South Korea's president−elect kidnapped by his own jakarta Shops burn in riot as students demand that government quit tokyo stock exchange Tokyo stocks mixed on receding hopes for stimulus package, dollar iraq Iraq tells Annan to be impartial in last−ditch peace mission Iraqi Kurds agree to exchange prisoners Annan leaves for Baghdad Gulf crisis keeping oil prices from sliding olympic gold medal Ld−Writethru,0566 NAGANO: the bronze. Hockey star is devastated by Canada's loss Rain forces cancellation of second heat of four−man bobsled Hasek shuts out Canada in shootout, Czechs advance to final Ld−Writethru,0503 Young Russian steals the show, becomes latest cross−country star Norway scores easy win as Japanese reign ends BULLETIN slalom and giant slalom Italy's Compagnoni wins third gold with ease hun sen ousted ranariddh Japanese envoy casts doubt on early Cambodian solution Cambodian military court sets date for Ranariddh's appearance hong kong's Customs officers arrest two men and seize 555,000 fake VCDs EU vice president calls for clear suffrage commitment in Hong Kong itar−tass news agency reported Belgian king thanks Yeltsin for welcome in Russia Nuclear reactor at power plant shuts down palestinian leader yasser arafat south korea human rights groups Group accuses officials of fueling anti−Chinese feelings Indonesia's new military chief warns of challenge as riot police president−elect kim dae−jung North Korea rejects ''six−nation joint declaration'' 1991 gulf war Report: Iraqis attack U.N. officers, take away their car Former defense minister: no chances of Iraqi attack on Israel iraq Marchers Protest action against Iraq Howard cancels overseas trip to follow movements in Gulf U.N. secretary−general 'rather optimistic' on Iraq talks U.N. secretary−general holds crucial talks with Iraqi leaders 20 injured as Jordanians clash with police in pro−Iraq protest U.N. has no food reserves in Iraq if war disrupts supplies Scattered pro−Iraq demonstrations in West Bank despite ban French foreign minister admits failed talks would end diplomatic Government gearing up to evacuate Filipinos from Middle East olympic gold medal Ld−Writethru,0512 Langen retains big lead in four−man heading into final run Germany wins men's closing relay of Olympic biathlon competition BULLETIN hong kong's Europeans: China seen as stability source in Asian crisis slalom and giant slalom Buraas wins men's slalom, Tomba watches from hotel room Olympics shaken by moderate earthquake indonesia's president suharto Report: Police claim they have uncovered plot to disrupt election Singapore paper: Suharto to postpone currency board nhl players Olympic gold medal match shows World Cup was no predictor iraq Annan plan could offer Iraq and U.S. a way out Foreign nationals preparing to leave Israel With Iraq Annan meets with Saddam for last−ditch talks to avert strike olympic gold medal Asians succeed in their neighborhood's Olympics Daehlie wins eighth gold Daehlie makes history while Russian women sweep secretary−general kofi annan Annan reaches agreement with Saddam in Baghdad Britain reacts cautiously to report of Iraq breakthrough U.N. spokesman: Annan on verge of breakthrough on Iraq indonesia's president suharto slalom and giant slalom hun sen ousted ranariddh Ranariddh's former military advisor denies fleeing Cambodia hong kong's Ethiopian Belay Wolashe wins New Airport Marathon nhl players south korea Englishman Edward Fryatt wins Malaysian Open palestinian leader yasser arafat Arafat hopeful of diplomatic resolution in Gulf Arafat hopeful of diplomatic resolution in Gulf; two injured in Netanyahu urges Russian against cooperation with Iran israeli Israeli planes rocket guerrilla bases in south Lebanon french president jacques chirac secretary−general kofi annan France says Annan took big step forward with Iraq agreement Yeltsin pleased with agreement between U.N. and Iraq Cook says if there is Iraq deal it's due to military pressure Despite Iraq pact, Palestinians keep up pro−Baghdad protests Olympic flame out, but afterglow burning bright Where was the thrill in Nagano? Olympic farewell: Images, stumbles _ and lots of weather iraqi president saddam hussein Israel worried that diplomatic solution won't eradicate Iraq Arab states welcome Annan accord to end Iraqi crisis Dates in Iraq's standoff over U.N. inspections hun sen ousted ranariddh Deposed premier's ally receives 10−year prison sentence strike iraq Jordanian troops arrest activists, seize arms in riot−hit city giant slalom kidnappers Shevardnadze agrees to talks with kidnappers's representative japanese foreign minister keizo obuchi arrived Yeltsin−Hashimoto meeting set for April 11−13 Clinton tells Israel Saddam will be forced to keep promises Palestinian official: Iraq emerged the winner India welcomes diplomatic breakthrough in Iraq Report: Israel had prepared response to Iraqi missile attack Israel had prepared response to Iraqi missile attack Yeltsin discusses Iraq deal with Chirac, Blair and U.N. chief Report: Two Kuwaitis released by Iraq return home Iraq trumpets victory, predicts quick lifting of sanctions Malaysian PM: Lift economic sanctions against Iraq Annan: smiles, waves as leaves Paris for New York Business as usual for U.S. soldiers _ along with hopes for peace Philippine president enters hospital for checkup, then meets Iraqi nagano olympics hun sen Two widows file suit against Hun Sen to fight for justice south korea Kim takes office with promises of democratic reforms hindu nationalist bharatiya janata party Court convenes legislature to test strength of rivals president fidel ramos palestinian leader yasser arafat kidnappers japanese foreign minister keizo obuchi arrived sri lanka Media watchdog asks government to punish guilty 1991 gulf war EU grants Iraq dlrs 11 million in humanitarian aid</figDesc><table coords="7,56.68,56.34,485.11,184.32">/16/1998 

02/17/1998 
02/18/1998 
02/19/1998 
02/20/1998 
02/21/1998 
02/22/1998 
02/23/1998 
02/24/1998 
02/25/1998 
02/26/1998 
02/27/1998 
02/28/1998 
03/01/clerides's 40.1 percent 

economic crisis 

farrakhan 

interfax news agency reported 

gas masks 

Israel has enough masks for tourists 

clap skates brought 

Clap, clap, clap not heard at the short track _ yet 

ayatollah mohammad yazdi 

Iranian cleric: U.S. wrestlers trip not a step toward diplomatic 
Cleric says arrival of U.S. wrestlers not a step toward diplomatic 

unprecedented dlrs 4.5 billion petrochemical joint venture 

China calls anew on West to refrain from attacking Iraq 

secretary general kofi annan 

nato−led peace force 

One American soldier injured in detonator explosion 
Three American soldiers, one Swede injured in detonator explosion 

pasha grishuk 

Grishuk−Platov win second straight gold 

montserrat living 
mysterious white fiat uno linked 
killed cabdriver zlatko popovic 
riyadh al−qaysi picked 
killed princess diana 
special commission 
hun sen 
yaounde's military hospital 
van roost 
chase millrose games 
san cristobal de las casas 
united states and britain 
security council resolutions 
united arab emirates 

Barge smuggling Iraqi diesel sinks off U.A.E. coast 

exit poll gave clerides 51 percent votes 
police say 
chinese traders 

armed forces 

south africa 

secretary−general kofi annan 

foreign minister mohammed saeed al−sahhaf 

France safer if it avoids striking Iraq, says minister 

clerides's 40.1 percent 

central bank 

Philippine stocks, peso strengthen 

los angeles 

worst economic crisis 

Indonesia's Suharto dismisses central bank governor amid economic 

gas masks 

world cup season 

end canada's seven−year reign atop women's ice hockey 

Ld−Writethru,0580 
Americans claim first women's ice hockey gold, 3−1 

san cristobal de las casas 

Mexican rebel supporters demanding implementation of peace accord 

president suharto installed 

Indonesian troops patrol as police warn rioters will be shot 

clap skates brought 

ayatollah mohammad yazdi 

farrakhan 

unprecedented dlrs 4.5 billion petrochemical joint venture 

swedish law 

Ld−Writethru,0718 
Ld−Writethru,0457 

japanese government 

Former Filipino sex slaves ask Japanese royals for help in 

montserrat living 
nato−led peace force 
princess diana's death 
yaounde's military hospital 
chase millrose games 
final 12 minutes 
exit poll gave clerides 51 percent votes 
united arab emirates 
united states and britain 

armed forces 

secretary−general kofi annan 

tokyo stock exchange 

Dollar higher in Tokyo, Japanese stocks retreat 

south africa 

hun sen 

Philippine president urges Sihanouk to return to Cambodia 
Deposed premier to return next month to prepare for polls: aide 

ayatollah ruhollah khomeini 

gas masks 

clerides's 40.1 percent 

suu kyi 

Philippine police halt protest against Burmese leader 

georgian president eduard shevardnadze 

unprecedented dlrs 4.5 billion petrochemical joint venture 

worst economic crisis 

interfax news agency reported 

dutch flower growers 

Dutch flower exporters criticize Japanese award bouquets 
Dutch flower exporters criticize Japanese bouquets 

italy's silvio fauner 

Daehlie gets record seventh gold as Norway edges Italy 
Ld−Writethru,0783 

vienna allegedly entered children's tents 

Police investigating sex abuse charges involving children 
title 

international monetary fund efforts 

Russian premier optimistic on loan after talks with IMF's 

end canada's seven−year reign atop women's ice hockey 
nato−led peace force 
japanese government 
official antara news agency 

Fire destroys 100 houses in Indonesian province 

southeast asian nations 
exit poll gave clerides 51 percent votes 
west bank 
world championship title games 
military strike 

olympic gold medal 

97 percent bosnian serbs 

deputy prime minister lee hsien loong 

Singapore will give Indonesia export guarantees only if other 
Singapore will give Indonesia export guarantees if other countries 
Singapore banks face 30 percent drop in 1997 earnings 

olympic ice hockey tournament 

sinn fein 

polling stations 

ayatollah ruhollah khomeini 

tomba fans 

Ld−Writethru,0675 
Ld−Writethru,0672 
SHIGA KOGEN: in 2:40.67. 

russian space station 

Two Russians, French astronaut return to Earth 
Two Russians, French astronaut depart Mir 

japanese troops 

Report: Japan says sex slave protest may result from 

dutch flower growers 

armed forces 

suu kyi 

left south africa 

west bank 

united nations resolutions 

interfax news agency reported 

leaking crude oil tanker permission 

Azores port denies entry to leaking oil tanker 
Lisbon port denies entry to leaking oil tanker 

india's foreign ministry quoted prime minister inder kumar gujral 

India tells French envoy that it opposes military strike against 
Ira,0250q 

arai 

Japanese lawmaker under investigation commits suicide 

14 parliamentary districts 

Precede NEW DELHI 
New polls ordered in violence−plagued eastern Indian state 

french president jacques chirac 

France optimistic about Annan mission to Baghdad 

tueting sprawled helplessly 
nato−led peace force 
official antara news agency 
italy's silvio fauner 
technology minister bacharuddin jusuf habibie 
vienna allegedly entered children's tents 
worst economic crisis 
powerful finance ministry 
world cup events 
canada's 18 
international monetary fund efforts 
world championship title games 
gold medalist gianni romme 

97 percent bosnian serbs 

mobutu sese seko 

Kabila visits Switzerland for ''private'' reasons 
Kabili visits Switzerland for ''private'' reasons 

worst economic crisis 

Australia rejects request for temporary entry to Indonesian 

deputy prime minister lee hsien loong 

sinn fein 

Sinn Fein to be expelled from Northern Ireland talks 

russian space station 

Mir's crew travels around station, successfully re−docks 

swedish ice hockey federation 

U.S. hockey players damaged rooms after losing 

broader tokyo stock price index 

121 polling stations 

iraqi president saddam hussein 

india's foreign ministry quoted prime minister inder kumar gujral 

India says no to use of its space against Iraq 

30−share philippine stock exchange index slipped 0.39 point 

Philippine shares end mixed; peso weakens on Rubin comments 
Philippine shares end mixed; peso weakens 

tomba fans 

dutch flower growers 

women's downhill monday 

airport spokesman yoshitaka tokoyoda 

Police say nothing found in suspicious suitcase at Japan's Narita 
POlice say nothing found in suspicious suitcase at Japan's Narita 

tokyo foreign exchange market 

Shares up 
Dollar higher against yen in Tokyo 

asian currencies 
civil aeronautics administration 
thrilling men's cross−country relay race 
tueting sprawled helplessly 
italy's silvio fauner 
leaking crude oil tanker permission 
vienna allegedly entered children's tents 
senior burmese officials 
arai 
united nations resolutions 
olympic record 

Former East German rowing coach under scrutiny in Britain 

canada's 18 
west bank 
powerful finance ministry 
world cup events 
world championship title games 

hun sen ousted ranariddh 

itar−tass news agency reported 

hindu nationalist bharatiya janata party 

Two people killed in bomb explosion. Heavy security for vote 

1991 gulf war 

president−elect kim dae−jung 

philippine traders 

south korea 

97 percent bosnian serbs 

deputy prime minister lee hsien loong 

sinn fein 

kidnappers 

Georgia vows peaceful end to U.N. hostage standoff 

congo president laurent kabila 

russian space station 

worst economic crisis 

Indonesian police arrest five accused of carrying gasoline bombs 

destroy iraq's secretive weapons program 

REPEATING to fix garble 
U.N.'s Annan begins crucial talks with Iraqi leaders 
Iraq urges America to stay out of Annan's peace mission 

tomba fans 

dutch flower growers 

india's foreign ministry quoted prime minister inder kumar gujral 

broader tokyo stock price index 

japanese foreign minister keizo obuchi arrived 

Japanese foreign minister holds talks with Russian leadership 
Japanese foreign minister arrives for talks with Russian 

world record 

George breaks women's pole vault record 

airport spokesman yoshitaka tokoyoda 
italy's silvio fauner 
portuguese navy corvette 
vienna allegedly entered children's tents 
arai 
world cup standings 
french president jacques chirac 
pink stucco guest house overlooking 

U.N.'s Annan holds crucial talks with Iraqi leaders 

dlrs 9.96 billion 
world war ii 
lee told parliament 
relay bronze 
powerful finance ministry 
human rights watch 

philippine traders 

deputy prime minister lee hsien loong 

worst economic crisis 

congo president laurent kabila 

kidnappers 

japanese prime minister ryutaro hashimoto 

Russian and Japanese foreign ministers reported to agree on Iraq 

international space station 

world cup standings 

121 polling stations 

chang 

Philippoussis upsets top seed Rios, to meet Chang for title 

united states 6−3 

Miller, McNeil advance to USTA Challenger final 

president boris yeltsin 

1991 gulf war 

Coalition provides political weight more than military muscle 

world record 

Gold for the Dutch, hope for the Americans 

tomba fans 

india's foreign ministry quoted prime minister inder kumar gujral 

president−elect kim dae−jung 

delta patriot missile battery 

Retransmitting to delete FEA designator 
Patriot missiles ready _ but U.S. troops hope they won't be fired 

lee told parliament 

Government warns Singaporeans against abusing maids 

vote counting begins march 2 

One killed in early voting in second phase of Indian elections. 

interfax news agency reported 

President released from hospital 

airport spokesman yoshitaka tokoyoda 
mapped iraq's presidential sites 
mass−circulation dong−a ilbo 
leaking crude oil tanker permission 
missile 

Cook says if there is Iraq deal, it's due to military pressure 
Mubarak hails UN−Iraqi agreement 
With Iraq 
U.S. air show presence cut 3rd time because of Saddam 
China expresses relief at Iraq settlement 
Annan signs deal with Iraq to ease crisis over U.S. strike 
Israel prefers diplomatic solution to Iraq crisis 
U.N. judge falls off horse, delays testimony of ex−U.N. commander 
Iraq says deal with U.N. is a defeat for America 
Britain says Saddam has ''moved a long way'' 

olympic gold medal 

nagano olympics 

30−share philippine stock exchange index slipped 0.39 point 

Philippine stocks, peso weaken 

1991 gulf war 

japanese prime minister ryutaro hashimoto 

Government spokesman: Japan didn't promise supplementary budget 

congo president laurent kabila 

worst economic crisis 

narita airport 

Police: False bomb threat made during Olympics 

taiwanese leaders 

Report: Taiwan's vice president on visit to Middle East 
Report: Taiwanese Vice President on visit to Middle East 

sri lanka 

Separatist rebels attack military convoy, up to 70 reported killed 

chang 

united states 6−3 

world record 

iraqi deputy prime minister tariq aziz 

Iraqis express relief, but fear attack could still occur 

japanese 

Weakened Asian tigers look for new Japanese investment 

delta patriot missile battery 
foreign ministry spokesman 
west bank 
palestinian police 
news agency ctk reported 
missile 
world cup race 
british foreign secretary robin cook 
including presidential palaces 

secretary−general kofi annan 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8" validated="false" coords="7,56.65,61.25,504.65,310.05"><figDesc coords="7,382.71,62.95,30.36,1.28;7,382.40,71.84,7.95,1.40;7,382.71,73.54,24.19,1.28;7,382.40,77.07,30.94,2.98;7,382.71,80.24,30.79,1.28;7,382.71,81.72,13.44,1.28;7,382.40,84.44,5.25,1.40;7,382.40,87.66,14.01,1.40;7,382.71,89.36,30.31,1.28;7,382.71,90.83,27.40,1.28;7,382.40,93.02,8.85,1.40;7,382.40,95.70,10.16,1.40;7,382.71,97.40,29.39,1.28;7,382.40,99.59,20.49,1.40;7,382.71,101.29,30.06,1.28;7,382.40,103.47,8.03,1.40;7,382.71,105.17,31.71,1.28;7,382.40,107.23,27.20,1.40;7,382.40,109.64,30.33,2.98;7,382.71,112.81,23.92,1.28;7,382.40,114.60,28.13,2.98;7,418.90,62.95,27.22,1.28;7,418.90,64.42,28.29,1.28;7,418.90,65.90,28.28,1.28;7,418.60,74.52,7.95,1.40;7,418.60,77.60,5.25,1.40;7,418.60,80.55,25.24,1.40;7,418.90,82.25,27.74,1.28;7,418.60,84.71,7.46,4.08;7,418.90,89.09,19.19,1.28;7,418.60,91.41,8.77,1.40;7,418.60,94.09,37.61,1.40;7,418.90,95.79,30.42,1.28;7,418.90,97.26,24.68,1.28;7,418.90,98.74,8.98,1.28;7,418.90,100.21,28.47,1.28;7,418.60,101.87,25.73,3.81;7,418.90,105.98,29.60,1.28;7,418.60,108.03,13.44,1.40;7,418.60,110.44,20.49,1.40;7,418.90,112.14,29.88,1.28;7,418.60,114.20,15.32,1.40;7,418.90,115.90,32.29,1.28;7,418.60,117.82,12.78,3.68;7,418.60,122.37,10.90,1.40;7,418.60,124.52,19.18,1.40;7,418.60,126.66,7.54,1.40;7,418.90,128.36,28.41,1.28;7,418.60,130.15,32.49,1.40;7,418.90,131.85,15.03,1.28;7,418.60,133.32,13.52,3.05;7,418.90,136.67,30.76,1.28;7,455.09,71.39,26.61,1.28;7,455.09,72.87,31.16,1.28;7,454.79,75.19,7.83,1.40;7,455.09,76.89,22.72,1.28;7,455.09,78.36,30.72,1.28;7,454.79,80.69,14.91,1.40;7,455.09,82.39,27.56,1.28;7,454.79,84.71,7.54,1.40;7,455.09,86.41,21.26,1.28;7,454.79,88.73,7.46,1.40;7,454.79,91.41,5.25,1.40;7,455.09,93.11,28.99,1.28;7,454.79,95.43,13.11,1.40;7,455.09,97.13,25.08,1.28;7,454.79,99.32,37.61,1.40;7,455.09,101.02,26.46,1.28;7,454.79,103.21,25.48,1.40;7,454.79,105.75,21.06,1.40;7,454.79,108.17,27.20,1.40;7,455.09,109.86,29.32,1.28;7,454.79,111.78,8.44,3.68;7,454.79,116.34,12.78,1.40;7,454.79,118.62,10.90,1.40;7,454.79,120.77,12.46,1.40;7,455.09,122.46,22.42,1.28;7,455.09,123.94,23.82,1.28;7,454.79,125.59,19.18,1.40;7,454.79,127.74,11.14,1.40;7,455.09,129.43,20.59,1.28;7,455.09,130.91,28.35,1.28;7,491.29,62.95,21.87,1.28;7,491.29,64.42,27.31,1.28;7,491.29,65.90,19.61,1.28;7,490.98,68.35,18.03,1.40;7,490.98,71.44,25.24,1.40;7,491.29,73.14,23.34,1.28;7,491.29,74.61,29.20,1.28;7,491.29,76.09,24.86,1.28;7,490.98,78.41,13.03,1.40;7,490.98,81.36,7.78,1.40;7,490.98,84.17,8.52,4.22;7,491.29,88.69,28.41,1.28;7,490.98,91.01,37.61,1.40;7,491.29,92.71,32.56,1.28;7,490.98,95.03,29.42,2.98;7,491.29,98.20,20.16,1.28;7,490.98,100.39,17.17,2.98;7,490.98,104.41,13.93,1.40;7,491.29,106.11,31.50,1.28;7,490.98,108.30,16.72,1.40;7,491.29,110.00,22.73,1.28;7,491.29,111.47,30.61,1.28;7,527.17,61.25,16.13,2.98;7,527.17,65.94,25.24,1.40;7,527.48,67.64,28.11,1.28;7,527.17,70.63,18.03,1.40;7,527.17,73.98,15.49,1.40;7,527.48,75.68,22.73,1.28;7,527.17,78.54,5.25,1.40;7,527.48,80.24,23.09,1.28;7,527.48,81.72,29.97,1.28;7,527.17,83.90,30.40,1.40;7,527.48,85.60,33.82,1.28;7,527.48,87.08,33.18,1.28;7,527.48,88.55,27.83,1.28;7,527.17,90.47,15.65,1.40;7,527.48,92.17,31.96,1.28;7,527.17,94.36,7.54,1.40;7,527.17,96.90,7.29,1.40;7,527.17,99.45,10.24,1.40;7,527.17,101.87,12.29,1.40;7,527.48,103.56,25.97,1.28;7,527.17,105.62,30.65,1.40;7,527.48,107.32,27.43,1.28;7,527.48,108.79,28.23,1.28;7,527.17,110.58,13.11,1.40;7,527.17,112.86,21.06,1.40;7,527.48,114.56,29.02,1.28;7,527.48,116.03,25.90,1.28;7,527.17,117.68,8.52,1.40;7,527.48,119.38,31.28,1.28;7,527.17,121.17,13.20,1.40;7,527.48,122.87,25.36,1.28;7,56.95,282.30,9.86,1.27;7,56.95,283.75,21.04,1.27;7,56.95,285.21,27.74,1.27;7,56.65,288.16,15.29,1.38;7,56.95,289.84,27.00,1.27;7,56.65,292.53,19.81,1.38;7,56.95,294.20,26.35,1.27;7,56.95,295.66,28.46,1.27;7,56.95,297.11,31.71,1.27;7,56.65,299.41,25.20,2.94;7,56.65,303.64,13.51,1.38;7,56.95,305.32,21.04,1.27;7,56.65,307.61,5.18,1.38;7,56.65,310.25,11.24,1.38;7,56.95,311.93,30.45,1.27;7,56.95,313.39,19.95,1.27;7,56.95,314.84,26.77,1.27;7,56.65,316.74,16.90,1.38;7,56.95,318.41,32.44,1.27;7,56.65,320.44,27.49,1.38;7,56.95,322.12,28.09,1.27;7,56.95,323.57,26.53,1.27;7,56.95,325.03,33.16,1.27;7,92.66,273.97,29.03,1.27;7,92.36,276.92,27.07,2.94;7,92.36,281.55,19.81,1.38;7,92.66,283.23,14.35,1.27;7,92.66,284.68,26.38,1.27;7,92.36,287.37,11.24,1.38;7,92.66,289.05,28.76,1.27;7,92.36,291.47,11.24,1.38;7,92.66,293.15,28.58,1.27;7,92.66,294.60,30.45,1.27;7,92.36,296.89,9.54,1.38;7,92.36,299.67,13.91,1.38;7,92.66,301.35,22.43,1.27;7,92.36,303.64,16.90,4.03;7,92.36,308.80,16.50,1.38;7,92.66,310.48,22.85,1.27;7,92.36,312.63,9.87,1.38;7,92.66,314.31,32.68,1.27;7,92.36,316.47,30.24,1.38;7,92.66,318.15,20.20,1.27;7,92.36,320.17,20.91,1.38;7,92.66,321.85,24.41,1.27;7,92.66,323.31,15.98,1.27">More Germans suspected of helping Libyan weapons program gold medals Queen welcomes winningest Dutch Olympic team kim Kim Dae−jung's honeymoon ends in legislative spat over prime Former dissident assumes South Korea's presidency, promises With BC−Skorea−President hun sen worst economic crisis Indonesian students rally against president, defying police ban Philippines to give medicine to cash−strapped Indonesia 1991 gulf war bjp government Reports: controversial governor in Indian state may get axed palestinian leader yasser arafat Mubarak, Arafat talk about Mideast peace as Iraq crisis eases saudi arabia Saudi septuplets' parents refuse to take them home from hospital israeli prime minister benjamin netanyahu dallaire Ex−U.N. commander in Rwanda says mission poorly supplied Ex−U.N. commander in Rwanda begins testifying israeli Army arrests six Palestinians in sweep of stone−throwers Iraqi parliament holds special session on U.N.−Iraq deal France, US supplied Iraq with anthrax spores in the 1980s Inspectors will work quickly under new accord, Butler says gold medals hun sen hindu nationalist bharatiya janata party Political test for Hindu nationalists amid general elections police north korea Four North Koreans defect to the South president kim israeli secret service mossad involving telephone bugging Furor in Israel over leaking of Mossad operation in Switzerland Swiss say suspected Mossad operation uncovered Precede GENEVA Swiss say suspected Mossad operation in Bern uncovered israel power supply company mercury energy Blacked−out New Zealand city to get back to work next week israeli troop pullback palestinian leader yasser arafat Palestinian population has grown to 2.89 million, census says receiving 29 million yen Widow of Japanese lawmaker abandons plan to run in by−election dallaire sunni muslim group langebaan prints nokia employs 36,600 people israeli radio Israel holding intensive contacts with Switzerland following tirana's high−security prison ended early thursday Prison riot ends with no injured title japanese companies New dlrs 1 billion undersea fiber−optic cable to link Japan, U.S. Anti−election strike, protest shut down Kashmiri capital Pakistan warns India's Hindu nationalists may destabilize region kim jong−pil Thailand's Chatchai retains WBC flyweight title Korea's rival political parties break impasse over prime minister tokyo stock price index Japanese stocks advance for third day, U.S. dollar drops nagano city Nagano Paralympics tickets almost sold out north korea hun sen Deposed Cambodian premier declares unilateral cease−fire summer's world cup European police officials plot anti−hooligan strategy israeli secret service mossad involving telephone bugging Report: Mossad agents made noise, alerted neighbors palestinians battered israeli army jeeps power company mercury energy israeli prime minister benjamin netanyahu Israeli prime minister to visit Norway, discuss peace process dallaire police official sunni muslim group langebaan prints yeo told parliament Singapore parliament bans political party films Singapore parliament bans all political party films nokia employs 36,600 people kurdish guerrillas Gunmen wound 16 Turkish soldiers in raid Gunmen raid military outpost in Turkey, wound 16 soldiers Two British journalists said missing in Bosnia Three policemen in northern Mexico arrested for alleged 13 killed as speeding train rams into bus iraq's deputy prime minister hindu nationalist bharatiya janata party First Exit Poll puts Hindu nationalist party ahead First Exit Poll puts Hindu nationalist party ahead, but by less Troops, protesters, but no voters in India's Kashmir weapons inspectors dlrs 4 billion nagano human rights Government revokes printing license of weekly newspaper israeli secret service mossad involving telephone bugging Bumps in the night are undoing of Israeli spy agency's Swiss caper israeli Israel accused of foot−dragging on bid for Pollard's freedom Smuggled arms intercepted on Dead Sea kim Webb leads after course record 64 burmese government More Burmese troops move into Thailand as stand−off continues southeast asian countries Ramos warns of Chinese currency devaluation Asian finance chiefs meet in Jakarta to discuss economic crisis oil Iraqis collect full ration for March hindu nationalist bharatiya janata party Counting of votes begins as India awaits new government iraq's deputy prime minister southeast asian nations ASEAN asking U.N. for help to fight forest fires hun sen Amnesty: political killings continue in Cambodia Khmer Rouge blasts Cambodian leader's cease−fire proposal lower saxony governor gerhard schroeder won Governor Schroeder wins re−election _ and chance to challenge Kohl Governor Schroeder wins reelection _ and chance to challenge Kohl Left−leaning state leader seeks chance to challenge Kohl united states and britain Libyan and Arab League officials meet to coordinate on Lockerbie nagano city local police burmese troops government troops Australian troops to stay in Gulf until U.N. satisfied on norwegian prime minister kjell magne bondevik Netanyahu to discuss peace efforts during trip to Europe Netanyahu to discuss peace process during trip to Europe summer's world cup israel's unconditional withdrawal Political momentum gathers for Israeli pullout from Lebanon Report: Syria wants to resume peace talks with Israel human rights Paper: U.N. human rights chief prevented from meeting Khatami 543 contested seats Election officials prepare to begin counting of ballots With India−Elections Indians wrestle with conscience to vote BJP Counting of votes begins as India awaits new government southeast asian nations U.S. military will aid Asian stability amid economic crisis: german chancellor helmut kohl In the fight against Kohl, this candidate represents new Kohl faces tough, telegenic adversary for German elections Germany's unemployment protesters call demonstration this week oil Strong economy boosts chemicals group's net profit human rights abuses Thai authorities curb East Timor conference hun sen kosovo albanians Unrest among ethnic Albanians raises fear of war in Yugoslavia Kosovo violence raises fears of wider war Police breaks up demonstration of thousands in Kosovo hasna mohammed humair Mother of Saudi septuplets wants help before she takes them home yeltsin's spokesman sergei yastrzhembsky Israel's Sharansky meets Russia premier for talks on trade Only 10 Russian officials to retain personal bodyguards Yeltsin names replacements to Cabinet members fired over weekend U.N. council agrees on warning to Iraq but no green−light for kim Korean president names close aide as intelligence chief german chancellor helmut kohl REPEAT to fix garbled coding Police blame anti−nuke protesters for railway sabotage president suharto U.S. envoy delivers Clinton's reform message to Indonesian kosovo albanians Tens of thousands attend funeral of slain Kosovo Albanians Unrest among ethnic Albanians raises fear of war in Yugoslavia congress party deputy prime minister Taiwan's vice president arrives for hushed visit oil hasna mohammed humair southeast asian countries Sri Lanka to lure American and British investors hun sen's army Trial of deposed Cambodian premier Norodom Ranariddh underway norwegian prime minister kjell magne bondevik Turkish president arrives in Spain for talks winter 1998−1999 italian fashion Safe styles, futuristic fabrics mark Milan collections Top models regain Italian runway</figDesc><table coords="7,56.65,61.25,484.05,310.05">expulsion 

delta patriot missile battery 
wife lien fang yu 
japanese minister 
iraq's 1990 invasion 
news agency ctk reported 
olympic history 
iraq fired 39 scud missiles 
weapons inspectors 

secretary−general kofi annan 

power supply company mercury energy 

sunni muslim group 

soldiers fired live ammunition 

langebaan prints 

Oldest human footprints, damagaed by modern man, to go to museum 
Oldest human footprints under man−made threat 

nokia employs 36,600 people 
kalandia refugee camp north 

Army arrests six Palestinians in sweep against stone−throwers 
PRECEDE Jerusalem 

general staff tang fei 

Taiwan's ex−air force chief promoted to chief of staff 
Taiwan ex−air force chief promoted to chief of staff 

north korea 

Aid group: North Korea expects to run out of food in April 

maryland murder suspect 

Judge proposes Sheinbein return to United States voluntarily 
In twist, defense lawyer says he disagrees with extradition law 

delta patriot missile battery 
wife lien fang yu 
illegal logging scandal 
missile 

Report: Israel asking U.S. for expanded anti−missile funding 

iraqi deputy prime minister tariq aziz 
news agency ctk reported 
weapons inspectors 

secretary−general kofi annan 

wife lien fang yu 
general staff tang fei 
illegal logging scandal 
iraqi missile attack 
israeli prime minister benjamin netanyahu 
maryland murder suspect 
soldier fired live bullets 
iraqi deputy prime minister tariq aziz 
regional economic crisis 

secretary−general kofi annan 

hindu nationalist bharatiya janata party 

opposition parties 
israeli radio 
general staff tang fei 
tirana's high−security prison ended early thursday 
receiving 29 million yen 
iraqi missile attack 
maryland murder suspect 
dlrs 7.8 billion 
people's action party 
west bank 

local police 

japanese stocks rose 

palestinians battered israeli army jeeps 

north korea 

hun sen 

Cambodians express cautious optimism about cease−fire 

summer's world cup 

oil fields 

government troops 

dallaire 

uttar pradesh's chief minister 

langebaan prints 
amer mohammed rashid 

Rashid: Iraq can't take full advantage of oil−for−food deal 
Rashid: Iraq can't take full advantage of oil−for−food 

dlrs 1.6 million 

Pacific Northwest Ballet takes leap of faith in 25th season 

yeo told parliament 
general staff tang fei 
tirana's high−security prison ended early thursday 
maryland murder suspect 
regional economic crisis 

U.S. commander stresses gravity of Indonesian situation 

political parties 
people's action party 
israel's foreign ministry 
west bank 

yeo told parliament 
kurdish guerrillas 
thai army 
political parties 
dlrs 20 million 
people's action party 

(a) 02/16/1998 -03/01/1998 

03/02/1998 
03/03/1998 
03/04/1998 
03/05/1998 
03/06/1998 
03/07/1998 
03/08/1998 
03/09/1998 
03/10/1998 
03/11/1998 
03/12/1998 
03/13/1998 
03/14/1998 
03/15/1998 

secretary−general kofi annan 

U.N. Council unanimously agrees on warning to Iraq 
U.S. envoy: Iraq singled out for inspections because of its record 

hindu nationalist bharatiya janata party 

ambassador nizar hamdoon 

U.S., Britain face opposition on Security Council warning to Iraq 
U.N. takes up U.S.−backed resolution on Iraq 

government troops 

Netanyahu sends envoys to Washington to try and block U.S. plan 

opium warlord khun sa 

norwegian prime minister kjell magne bondevik 

safari rally 

Britain's Burns wins Safari Rally 

saudi arabia 
united states and britain 
south lebanon 
malaysia's prime minister 

Malaysia says mass repatriation will not affect ASEAN ties 

exit poll results 
thai army 

secretary−general kofi annan 

trade minister tim fischer 

Report: Asian crisis to hit Australian jobs next year 
Australian report: new barriers threaten world trade, including 
Report: Asian crisis to hit Australian jobs in late 98/99 

cape town 

Possible breakthrough in case of slain Swedish tourists 

security council 

Yeltsin merges security agencies, appoints new chief 
France vague on ''severest consequences''; air strike debate 

dlrs 4 billion 

poll broadcast 

luggage handlers staged short walkouts 

Precede BONN 
Massive public worker strike delays German commuters, air travel 

1991 council resolution 

U.N. council agrees on warning to Iraq 

5 million greek orthodox 

Improvement in condition of ailing Greek Orthodox leader 

united states and britain 
israel's unconditional withdrawal 
u.n.−approved oil−for−food program 
president bill clinton 
interfax news agency reported 
ambassador nizar hamdoon 
major blocs began holding strategy sessions 

iraq 

Iraqi foreign minister due for talks on oil−for−food program 

mossad agents 

Netanyahu appoints Halevy as Mossad chief 
Israeli officials deny report of Swiss assassination attempt 
Report: Netanyahu to appoint Jordan mediator as Mossad chief 

german chancellor helmut kohl 

bosnian serbs 

Serb war crimes suspect blames politicians 

israeli prime minister benjamin netanyahu 

Norway wants Mideast sides to respect Oslo agreement 

kosovo albanians 

hun sen's forces 

Court finds deposed Cambodian premier guilty of arms smuggling 

security council 

bharatiya janata party 

north korea 

South Korea hints at early shipments of food aid to North Korea 

norwegian prime minister kjell magne bondevik 

party won 

Inconclusive election leads to jockeying for power 

dlrs 5.2 billion 

Fast economy halts oil investments 

winter 1998−1999 italian fashion 

trade minister tim fischer 

babies home 

united states and britain 

cape town 

deputy prime minister 

won weizman 

Weizman re−elected as Israel's president 
JERUSALEM: legislators abstained. 

noor ahmed shah 

Flash floods kill at least 75, another 250 people missing 

puerto rico 

Puerto Ricans wary of U.S. status deliberations 
With Puerto Rico−Status 

luggage handlers staged short walkouts 
5 million greek orthodox 
major blocs began holding strategy sessions 
saudi arabia 

Relative: No clue when British nurses will be freed 

israel's unconditional withdrawal 
ambassador nizar hamdoon 
president bill clinton 
interfax news agency reported 

iraq 

Delays still hamper Iraq's oil−for−food program 
U.N. team under American Scott Ritter on its way to Iraq 

kosovo albanians 

PRISTINA: restore calm. 
With BC−Yugoslavia−Kosovo 
PRISTINA: Thursday's sweep. 
Serb police announce 20 ''terrorists'' killed in crackdown. 
Ethnic Albanian militants threaten revenge on Serbs 
British Foreign Secretary to warn Yugoslav president on Kosovo 

prime minister benjamin netanyahu 

itar−tass news agency 

Confederation expels controversial Chechen warlord 
Lebed given spot on ballot for Siberian governorship 

mossad agents 

Swiss police reportedly looking for missing Lebanese man 

bharatiya janata party 

Socialist who may join India's government wants multinationals out 

bosnian serbs 

hun sen 

Philippines urges Hun Sen to abide by Japanese election proposal 

president suharto 

yeltsin's spokesman sergei yastrzhembsky 

Russia keeps up chorus of protest against Latvia 

world court 

Cameroon urges World Court to end territorial dispute 

north korea 

Report: Documents show spy agency operated against Kim 

hasna mohammed humair 

Saudi mother of septuplets not ready to cope with newborns 

winter 1998−1999 italian fashion 

trade minister tim fischer 

emergency power 

In Auckland's heart of darkness, businesses at risk of going under 

won weizman 
noor ahmed shah 
luggage handlers staged short walkouts 
deputy prime minister 
puerto rico 
security council 
food 
butler told cnn 
interfax news agency reported 

kosovo albanians 

Annan expresses concern over Kosovo but UN to take a back seat for 
Serb special police press Kosovo crackdown 
Serb special police continue their crackdown in part of Kosovo 
Serb police kill 20 Albanians in crackdown on separatists. 

iraq 

American U.N. expert starts his first day of weapons inspections in 

israeli prime minister benjamin netanyahu 

Israeli leader arrives in Norway 
Former army chief says as Palestinian, he'd have been a terrorist 
Israeli leader holds talks with Kohl in Germany 
Contradictory polls suggest public confused over Lebanon 

itar−tass news agency 

mossad agents 

After Mossad scandal fades, another spy agency hits headlines 

world cup tickets 

PRECEDE Brussels 
French to hold on to tickets; foreigners condemned to small share 
French to hold on to tickets; foreign fans condemned to small 

hun sen 

currency board plan 

Report: Indonesia to decide economic plan after election 
As rupiah slides, Indonesia's Suharto meets economic team 

bosnian serbs 

north korea 

Seoul says no evidence to support rumors of unrest in North Korea 

hans van den broek 

EU Commissioner leaves without breakthrough 
AP photo NIC−101 available 

world cup finals 

Final session canceled because of heavy snowfall 

philippine stock exchange index 

Asian stock markets close generally mixed 

state madeleine albright 

Ukraine cancels nuclear deal with Iran, pleases U.S. 
U.S. wins Ukrainian pledges of export controls 

broader tokyo stock price index 

trade minister tim fischer 

security council 

won weizman 
noor ahmed shah 
luggage handlers staged short walkouts 
emergency power 
puerto rico 
potential weapons sites 

American Ritter resumes inspections in Iraq 

80 percent 
interfax news agency reported 

kosovo albanians 

Repeat 
Serbia's Kosovo crisis raises fears in other parts of Europe 
Federal president predicts 'slaughterhouse' in Kosovo 
International watchdog seeks probe into possible war crimes in 
Albright demands ''firm action'' against Serbia 
Serbian police: Search for 'terrorists' still on in Kosovo 
Albright issues warnings to Serbia, Iraq 

israeli prime minister benjamin netanyahu 

Netanyahu expresses vague optimism after Oslo talks 

weapons inspectors 

King Hussein tones down proposal for U.S.−Iraqi dialogue 
American−led team inspects suspected weapons sites 

world cup 

Brazil's Scherer sets South American record in 50 fly 
France's Burtin wins first DH; Maier clinches overall 

mossad agents 

human rights 

world cup tickets 

north korea 

security council 

puerto rico 

Several homes flooded by heavy rains 
NASA to renew rocket launches 

hans van den broek 

currency board plan 

broader tokyo stock price index 

unseeded siemerink gave krajicek 

Siemerink knocks lackluster Krajicek 
Siemerink knocks lackluster Krajicek out of ABN AMRO indoor 
Siermerink knocks lackluster Krajicek out of ABN AMRO indoor 

reigning world cup champion nicolas fontaine 

Canada's Nicolas Fontaine wins freestyle aerials competition,0308 
Canada's Nicolas Fontaine wins freestyle aerials competition 
competition,0308 

told conference organizer kirby jones 

American businessmen look with longing at Cuba 
Cuba urges U.S. businesses to oppose trade embargo 

palestinian leader yasser arafat 

Excerpts from Yasser Arafat's speech to lawmakers 
Lawmakers lambaste Arafat for failing to follow up reform pledges 

president aslan maskhadov 

Chechnya: Release British hostages before president goes to London 

peace 

state madeleine albright 

ahson 

Police say man who married for love should be freed 

emergency power 
russian−designed nuclear reactors 

Iran says Ukraine big loser for pulling out of nuclear deal 

italian foreign minister lamberto dini 
russian ambassador sergey lavrov 

kosovo albanians 

Demonstrations planned in Kosovo, world powers meet on crisis. 
Serbs declare Kosovo siege over 
Albania calls Moscow biased over Kosovo 
Serbian police say Kosovo siege over 
Precede PRISTINA 
Serbian police maintain seal around targeted villages 
Pope decries violence in Kosovo, oppression of women 
Ethnic Albanians in Turkey protest Serb attacks in Kosovo 

israeli prime minister benjamin netanyahu 

Netanyahu ends four−nation Europe swing; Blair to visit 
Austrian investors seek to build casino in Jericho 
Netanyahu to present Blair with plan to reactivate peace process 

weapons inspectors 

bharatiya janata party 

Hindu nationalists inch closer to power 

world cup 

chechnya's two−year war 

Chechen president, headed for Britain, unharmed in car accident 

itar−tass news agency 

Three Chechens killed, livestock saved in gun battle 

suharto 

As outsiders worry, Indonesian legislators put confidence in 
Suharto sees conflict between IMF reform and constitution: 

world cup tickets 

human rights 

broader tokyo stock price index 

Dollar, Japanese stocks rise in morning Tokyo trading 

israeli troops 

hans van den broek 

US envoy arrives to promote resumption of stalled peace talks 

security council 

monday israel's trade minister natan sharansky 

Israel's Sharon meets Jordanian leaders for talks on projects 
Israel's Sharon arrives in Jordan for talks on joint projects 

party won 

unseeded siemerink gave krajicek 

reigning world cup champion nicolas fontaine 

currency board plan 

state madeleine albright 

told conference organizer kirby jones 

peace 

royal highness 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9" validated="false" coords="7,54.00,272.29,504.04,441.53"><figDesc coords="8,203.22,699.68,3.38,12.24;8,203.22,690.01,3.38,8.86;8,203.22,683.89,3.38,5.32;8,203.22,676.64,3.38,6.45;8,203.22,673.42,3.38,2.42;8,203.22,665.04,3.38,7.57;8,203.22,655.21,3.38,9.02;8,203.22,644.27,3.38,10.14;8,211.10,699.11,3.69,13.61;8,211.10,691.54,3.69,6.48;8,211.10,679.45,3.69,11.02;8,215.59,699.52,3.38,12.40;8,215.59,685.18,3.38,13.53;8,215.59,672.94,3.38,11.43;8,215.59,667.30,3.38,4.83;8,215.59,664.08,3.38,2.42;8,215.59,660.05,3.38,3.22;8,215.59,652.97,3.38,6.28;8,223.12,707.89,7.86,4.83;8,227.60,700.97,3.38,6.12;8,227.60,697.74,3.38,2.42;8,227.60,692.91,3.38,4.03;8,227.60,681.96,3.38,10.15;8,227.60,673.74,3.38,7.41;8,227.60,670.52,3.38,2.42;8,227.60,662.62,3.38,7.09;8,227.60,655.86,3.38,5.96;8,227.60,648.45,3.38,6.60;8,227.60,627.91,3.38,19.73;8,231.49,704.03,3.38,7.89;8,231.49,697.74,3.38,5.48;8,231.49,688.24,3.38,8.70;8,231.49,683.41,3.38,4.03;8,231.49,676.00,3.38,6.61;8,231.49,672.77,3.38,2.42;8,231.49,664.24,3.38,7.73;8,231.49,652.48,3.38,10.95;8,231.49,646.52,3.38,5.15;8,231.49,636.86,3.38,8.86;8,235.38,703.22,3.38,8.70;8,235.38,697.58,3.38,4.83;8,235.38,688.88,3.38,7.89;8,235.38,676.48,3.38,11.60;8,235.38,668.75,3.38,6.93;8,235.38,663.92,3.38,4.03;8,235.38,656.83,3.38,6.28;8,235.38,653.61,3.38,2.42;8,235.38,643.94,3.38,8.86;8,235.38,633.79,3.38,9.34;8,239.26,702.41,3.38,9.50;8,239.26,693.07,3.38,8.53;8,239.26,677.45,3.38,14.81;8,239.26,667.63,3.38,9.02;8,239.26,653.77,3.38,13.05;8,239.26,647.17,3.38,5.80;8,245.38,699.33,3.69,13.39;8,245.38,686.15,3.69,12.10;8,249.87,706.92,3.38,4.99;8,249.87,697.58,3.38,8.53;8,249.87,684.21,3.38,12.56;8,249.87,670.36,3.38,13.05;8,249.87,658.28,3.38,11.27;8,249.87,642.17,3.38,15.31;8,249.87,630.57,3.38,10.79;8,253.75,698.87,3.38,13.05;8,253.75,689.85,3.38,8.22;8,253.75,686.79,3.38,2.25;8,253.75,678.25,3.38,7.73;8,253.75,675.03,3.38,2.42;8,253.75,667.62,3.38,6.61;8,253.75,651.03,3.38,15.79;8,253.75,643.78,3.38,6.44;8,260.58,700.19,3.69,12.53;8,260.58,683.12,3.69,15.99;8,260.58,673.62,3.69,8.42;8,260.58,661.52,3.69,11.02;8,265.06,703.22,3.38,8.70;8,265.06,695.65,3.38,6.76;8,265.06,686.79,3.38,8.06;8,265.06,678.41,3.38,7.57;8,265.06,668.75,3.38,8.86;8,268.95,703.22,3.38,8.70;8,268.95,700.00,3.38,2.42;8,268.95,692.91,3.38,6.28;8,268.95,682.12,3.38,9.99;8,268.95,671.00,3.38,10.31;8,268.95,666.97,3.38,3.22;8,268.95,653.21,3.38,12.96;8,268.95,641.61,3.38,10.79;8,121.23,608.93,3.38,7.57;8,121.23,602.01,3.38,6.12;8,121.23,588.31,3.38,12.89;8,121.23,580.58,3.38,6.93;8,121.23,574.46,3.38,5.32;8,121.23,567.53,3.38,6.12;8,121.23,561.41,3.38,5.32;8,121.23,544.67,3.38,15.94;8,125.11,610.86,3.38,5.64;8,125.11,601.68,3.38,8.38;8,125.11,594.27,3.38,6.60;8,125.11,587.83,3.38,5.64;8,125.11,582.19,3.38,4.83;8,125.11,570.75,3.38,10.63;8,125.11,566.88,3.38,3.06;8,125.11,562.70,3.38,3.38;8,125.11,558.51,3.38,3.38;8,125.11,550.14,3.38,7.57;8,125.11,544.02,3.38,5.32;8,125.11,531.45,3.38,11.76;8,143.60,604.58,7.86,12.73;8,148.09,595.72,3.38,8.05;8,148.09,586.05,3.38,8.86;8,148.09,582.83,3.38,2.42;8,148.09,576.07,3.38,5.96;8,148.09,569.62,3.38,5.64;8,148.09,558.35,3.38,10.47;8,148.09,553.51,3.38,4.03;8,148.09,539.34,3.38,13.37;8,148.09,534.35,3.38,4.18">American named new head of South African Airways ethiopia and eritrea Eritreans, Ethiopians welcome end to air raids eu EU back to the drawing board to make itself more people−friendly Greek veto dooms EU effort to revive relations with Turkey Money and power wrangles cloud EU drive to reunite Europe Finland ratifies Amsterdam Treaty, Schengen Pact security council Iraq rejects resolution stipulating longterm oil−for−food program Delegates gather in Rome to forge international court russian president boris yeltsin Yeltsin won't attend czar's funeral Yeltsin to chair Cabinet meeting on anti−crisis program World Cup: Hooligans could lose jobs, club membership Thai police: More than 100 arrested so far for World Cup gambling kosovo Yugoslav leader agrees to talks over Kosovo, but settlement still</figDesc><table coords="7,54.00,272.29,504.04,441.53">Istanbul 
Police breaks up demonstration, tens injured in stampede 

crew members found diving gear belonging 

Tourism official applauds charges against tour boat operator 

palestinian leader yasser arafat 
dlrs 43 billion economic bailout 
palestinian economy 
ritter's team 

U.N. team has visited six 'sensitive' sites 

pope john paul ii 
russian−designed nuclear reactors 
italian foreign minister lamberto dini 
russian ambassador sergey lavrov 

kosovo albanians 

Kosovo protests killing; relatives refuse bodies, demand autopsy 
Conference on Kosovo adopts immediate and longer−term measures 
Greece condemns 'secessionist tendencies' and repression in Kosovo 
Bosnian Serb pleads guilty to rape at war crimes tribunal 
Largest demonstration in 10 years in Kosovo as world powers meet 
Largest demonstration in 10 years in Kosovo as powers meet 
Germany says no suspension of deportations to Kosovo 

israeli prime minister benjamin netanyahu 

Jordan to ask Israel to abide by peace accords 
Egyptian president: Netanyahu hasn't kept any promises 

suharto 

Indonesia's President Suharto: Asia's longest serving leader 
Indonesia's Suharto gets new powers, is re−elected 

security council 

chechnya's two−year war 

north korea 

South Korean Red Cross proposes meeting with northern counterpart 

breakaway turkish cypriot state 

AP Photo available 

northern ireland 

Government frees IRA suspect wanted in Germany over mortar attack 
Adams keeps Sinn Fein out of Belfast talks until he meets Blair 

world cup tickets 

world cup 

israeli 

Government will step up efforts to free Pollard 

palestinian leader yasser arafat 

Opposition chancellor candidate to visit Israel, Lebanon 

teammate david coulthard 

FIA rejects Australian GP protest but could ban arranged finishes 

monday israel's trade minister natan sharansky 

Israel's Sharansky meets Jordanian king, signs trade accords 

hindu nationalist party 

kurdish rebel group pkk 

Report: Turkish Kurdish rebels may withdraw from northern Iraq 

dlrs 43 billion economic bailout 

Japan Minister: No plans to delay aid earmarked for Indonesia 

party won 

unseeded siemerink gave krajicek 

reigning world cup champion nicolas fontaine 

state madeleine albright 

told conference organizer kirby jones 

suspected weapons sites 

peace 

al−rai al−amm daily quoted sheik sabah al−ahmed al−sabah 

Kuwait wants Iraq to admit invasion was a mistake, report 
Kuwait wants Iraq to admit invasion was a mistake, minister says 

trevor francis 

Birmingham City manager withdraws resignation 

german foreign minister klaus kinkel 
pope john paul ii 
royal highness 
ethiopian−born saudi financier sheikh mohamed hussein al amoudi 
romanian 5,000−meter world champion ran 
crew members found diving gear belonging 
russian−designed nuclear reactors 
turkish foreign minister ismail cem 
united front 

kosovo 

Don't underrate Western powers, Britain tells Milosevic 
Kosovo protests killing; relatives refuse bodies, demand autopsy 
War Crimes Court says it is investigating Kosovo violence 
In Kosovo, like Bosnia, Russia seeks to soften sanctions against 

president suharto 

Chinese leaders congratulate Indonesia's Suharto 

israeli prime minister benjamin netanyahu 

Militant uses Israeli opposition leader's comments to justify acts 

itar−tass news agency 

Nearly 1,000 people hurt in falls on Moscow ice 
Moscow mayor intent on restricting capital residents 
Precede MOSCOW 

saudi arabia's king fahd 

Fahd in stable condition after undergoing gall bladder surgery 
Fahd in stable condition after gall bladder surgery 

downhill 

Ld−Writethru,0699 
Ld−Writethru 
Street ambivalent about end to her ''roller coaster'' season 

cyprus 

Survey: offshore sector to shrink after Cyprus EU membership 

broader tokyo stock price index 

Japanese stocks fall, dollar edges higher in Tokyo 

chechnya's two−year war 

Commission should determine if Russia has claim to Chechnya 

bharatiya janata party 

How India's BJP may win the majority 
Gandhi widow weighs political offer, as BJP musters needed support 

northern ireland 

peace 

north korea 

teammate david coulthard 

war crimes tribunal 

israeli 

Israeli soldiers fire on Palestinian van at roadblock 

security council resolutions 

Head of Joints Chiefs says US troops ready to stay in Kuwait 

nuclear waste 

Standoff continues over shipload of nuclear waste 
Governor bars ship carrying nuclear waste, protesters keep vigil 

unseeded siemerink gave krajicek 

reigning world cup champion nicolas fontaine 

world cup 

jordanian crown prince hassan 

kurdish rebel group pkk 

alicia alvarez gutierrez 

Six months after Hurricane Pauline, Acapulco still struggling 

al−rai al−amm daily quoted sheik sabah al−ahmed al−sabah 
royal highness 
trevor francis 
romanian 5,000−meter world champion ran 
cuba paid 
german foreign minister klaus kinkel 
crew members found diving gear belonging 
palestinian leader yasser arafat 
pope john paul ii 
palestinian parliament 

kosovo albanians 

Albanians rebury victims; militants warn of new strikes 
Prodi confirims Italy to back sanctions if Serbia doesn't allow 
Kosovo's Albanians, outraged at common grave, rebury their dead 
Russian Duma defends Serbs over Kosovo conflict 
Kosovo's Albanians to rebury their dead 
International Red Cross receives threats, pulls back foreign staff 
Kosovo's Albanians try to rebury their dead; U.S. envoy holds 

israeli prime minister benjamin netanyahu 

Report: Annan bringing proposal for Israeli troop withdrawal from 

human rights 

Ailing Chinese dissident's parents appeal for his release 
China to sign U.N. covenant on civil and political rights 
Philippine government, Communist rebels agree on human rights 
Turkish court acquits 10 policemen in torture case 

president suharto 

Speculation turns to make−up of new Indonesian cabinet 
Australian aid conditional on Indonesia accepting IMF program 
Former Cabinet minister chosen as deputy to Indonesia's Suharto 
Philippine president: Suharto's re−election will help Indonesia's 

itar−tass news agency 

eu 

EU using money and diplomacy to revive Mideast peace process 
Spain to fight EU plans to place quotas on olive production 
EU Commission adopts strategy on freer EU−US trade 

meet british prime minister tony blair 

Police crack down on alleged killers of Protestant, Catholic 
Germany, denied extradition, asks Britain to prosecute IRA suspect 

world cup 

downhill title 

Downhill winner crowned, but World Cup victory still coveted 

israeli 

In West Bank, burying the dead and bracing for new battle 
Clashes in West Bank following roadblock shooting 

saudi arabia's king fahd 

broader tokyo stock price index 

breakaway turkish cypriot state 

palestinian leader yasser arafat 

Italian President cancels trips to Israel and Syria 

north korea 

myanmar military 

With AP Photos 
Karen refugees rebuilding camp in wake of attack 

auckland's mercury energy 

Anger mounts over blackout; lawsuits and protest march in works 

nyrup rasmussen 

Social Democrats win narrow victory in cliffhanger election 
Exit poll shows Social Dems, trying for reelection, in virtual dead 

australian grand prix 

kuwait wants iraq 

Paper: Iraq won't accept Kuwaiti conditions for peace 

jordanian crown prince hassan 

kurdish rebel group pkk 

thai government 

Singapore's DBS acquires Thailand's Thai Danu Bank 

police station 
al−rai al−amm daily quoted sheik sabah al−ahmed al−sabah 
nuclear waste 
trevor francis 
alicia alvarez gutierrez 
romanian 5,000−meter world champion ran 
pope john paul ii 
west bank town 
military police 
dlrs 43 billion economic bailout 

kosovo albanians 

Ethnic Albanians reject Serb 
b 

03 02 1998 03 15 1998 

F gu e 3 S o y flow v sua za on o ca cu a ed hemes and documen ass gnmen s o each day w h n a ou week pe od om he TDT 2 
APW Co pus 

6 S Hav e B He z e and L Nowe ThemeR ve V sua z ng heme 
changes ove me n EEE Sympos um on n orma on V sua za on 
2000 n oV s 2000 pages 115–123 2000 
7 S Hav e E He z e P Wh ney and L Nowe ThemeR ve v sua 
z ng hema c changes n a ge documen co ec ons EEE ransac 
ons on v sua za on and compu er graph cs 8 1 9–20 2002 
8 E He z e V C ow D Payne and A Tu ne Tu n ng he Bucke o 
Tex n o a P pe n EEE Sympos um on n orma on V sua za on 
2005 NFOV S 2005 pages 89–94 2005 
9 K Jones A S a s ca n e p e a on o Te m Spec fic y and s Ap 
p ca on n Re eva Journa o Documen a on 28 1 11–21 1972 
10 S Jones and G Payn e Top c based b ows ng w h n a d g a b a y 
us ng keyph ases n DL 99 Proceed ngs o he our h ACM con er 
ence on D g a brar es pages 114–121 New Yo k NY USA 1999 
ACM 
11 J Leskovec L Backs om and J K e nbe g Meme ack ng and 
he Dynam cs o he News Cyc e n Proceed ngs o he 15 h ACM 
S GKDD n erna ona con erence on Know edge d scovery and da a 
m n ng pages 497–506 ACM New Yo k NY USA 2009 
12 S Rose D Enge N C ame and W Cow ey Tex M n ng chap 
e Au oma c Keywo d Ex ac on om nd v dua Documen s John 
W ey and Sons L d 2009 o appea 
13 G Sa on A Wong and C S Yang A vec o space mode o au o 
ma c ndex ng Commun ACM 18 11 613–620 1975 

14 B N Sch and O Ko ak Exp o ng a d g a b a y h ough key 
deas n JCDL 08 Proceed ngs o he 8 h ACM EEE CS o n con 
erence on D g a brar es pages 177–186 New Yo k NY USA 
2008 ACM 
15 E Tu e and D Rob ns V sua exp ana ons G aph cs P ess Chesh e 
Conn 1997 
16 F V egas S Go de and J Dona h V sua z ng ema con en po 
ay ng e a onsh ps om conve sa ona h s o es n Proceed ngs 
o he S GCH con erence on Human Fac ors n compu ng sys ems 
pages 979–988 ACM New Yo k NY USA 2006 
17 F V egas M Wa enbe g and K Dave S udy ng coope a on and 
confl c be ween au ho s w h h s o y flow v sua za ons n Proceed 
ngs o he S GCH con erence on Human ac ors n compu ng sys 
ems pages 575–582 ACM New Yo k NY USA 2004 
18 J Wa d J H e a ch ca g oup ng o op m ze an ob ec ve unc on 
Journa o he Amer can s a s ca assoc a on pages 236–244 1963 06/15/1998 

06/16/1998 

06/17/1998 

06/18/1998 

06/19/1998 

06/20/1998 

06/21/1998 

world cup 

World Cup: Moeller header puts Germans 1−0 ahead at halftime 
World Cup: Romania beats Colombia 1−0 
World Cup: France guards against concentration lapse ahead of Saudi 
World Cup: unconvincing win sobers Yugoslavs 

kosovo 

EU adds ban on commercial flights to Serbia sanctions over Kosovo 
Macedonians say NATO action brings sense of security 

nato 

Officials disagree on whether U.N. mandate needed for Kosovo 
Russian defense minister rebukes U.S. commander over Kosovo 
NATO allies trying to give Milosevic a lesson in power 
UNHCR says helicopters may be used to help Kosovo refugees 
Some Albanians say NATO shor of force is not enough 

south africa's 

zedillo 
moshood abiola 
english fans 

World Cup: English fans celebrate in Spain 
Violence flares again after England beats Tunisia 
English, Tunisian fans clash, thwarting police measures 
Government leaders condemn 'disgrace' of English troublemakers 

World Cup: English hooligans back in business 

portuguese colony 

interfax news agency 

Seventy−two forest fires registered near Moscow over weekend 

frank de boer 
tunisia chokri el ouaer 

World Cup: In eye of the storm, England beats Tunisia 2−0 
World Cup: England leads Tunisia 1−0 at halftime 

detainees and all prisoners 

Nigerian junta frees nine prominent political detainees 
URGENT 

national team 

NBA players might be bounced from U.S. roster 

mario stanic put 
portuguese news agency lusa reported 
paraguay jose luis chilavert 

shin bet chief ami ayalon recently withdrew 
french world cup organizing committee 
detroit red wings 
newly reconstituted police forces 

Council meeting on Bosnia, expected to approve U.N. mission for a 

butler 

Chief inspector: Iraq close to being free from U.N. sanctions 

palestinian authority 

gave woodforde a second break 
brian laudrup sliced open 
jordan 
tickets 
military leader urged 

5.2 seconds left 
defense secretary william cohen 
saudi arabia 

world cup 

More influence for Montenegro reformists in Yugoslav parliament 
Milosevic agrees to negotiate with moderate Kosovo Albanian leader 
Milosevic refuses to negotiate with KLA, says not affected by NATO 
Milosevic agrees to negotiate over Kosovo political leader 

nato 
eu 

EU leaders to urge Indonesia to free East Timor leader 
Clinton phone call fails to lift EU−Turkey ties from deep freeze 
EU says goodbye to Mandela _ amid plaudits and trade prods 
EU bans fish, mollusk imports from Turkey 

security council 
russian president boris yeltsin 

Kremlin and Moscow sign power−sharing agreement 
Government to launch program to help coal miners 

portuguese colony 

eritrea 

Ethiopia deports 500 Eritreans 

detroit red wings 

EDs: Combines previous and updates with quotes 
Yzerman grabs two trophies as Red Wings win Cup 

Red Wings sweep Capitals to win Stanley Cup 

south african president nelson mandela 

Soweto uprising remembered in rallies, peaceful gunfire 

english fans 
weak yen 

Dollar weaker, Tokyo stocks higher in morning trading 

interfax news agency 
frank de boer 
usa basketball 

NBA players bounced from U.S. roster 

germany's chancellor kohl 

_REPEAT FOR ALL NEEDING_ 
Summit budget battle sidelines launch of 'people's Europe', 

sunday's game 

World Cup: Valiant loss gives Japan confidence against Croatia 

west bank 

Israel says Palestinians stealing beehives 

late dictator gen 
mario stanic put 
shin bet chief ami ayalon recently withdrew 
tunisia chokri el ouaer 
detainees and all prisoners 

dlrs 200 million 

World Bank mission reviews programs in Ukraine 
Xerox to invest up to dlrs 30 million in Russia before 2000 

national team 

A mighty track team, and a turbulent time 

jordan 
butler 
increasingly popular gambling vehicle 

Thai police: more than 100 arrested so far for World Cup gambling 

5.2 seconds left 
palestinian authority 

world cup game 

Iran coach: Iran−US both need win in their big match to advance in 
World Cup: Late Vastic strike earns Austria another 1−1 tie 
Belgian captain Van der Elst injured in training 
Asprilla dismissed from squad 
World Cup: Croatian captain pulls muscle, out for Japan game 
Consultant, two others arrested in ticket scam case 

kosovo 

Montenegro distances itself from Milosevic's Kosovo policy 
Albanian president calls border shootings a provocation 

eu 
security council 

Resolution submitted on Iraq spare parts 

U.S. opposes independent world court prosecutor 

russian president boris yeltsin 

Emergency program, Chubais' possible appointment to fight crisis 
Russian government defends plans for czar's funeral 

tokyo stock exchange 

Dollar plunges against yen in Tokyo, stocks rally 
London share prices higher at midday 

english fans 
eritrean capital asmara 
detroit red wings 

Red Wings cap memorable season with a memorable finals 

south african president nelson mandela 
coach aime jacquet 

World Cup: French heavily favored against desperate Saudis 

prominent political prisoners 

An angry Nigerian dissident, worn after prison term, returns home 

interfax news agency 

au pair louise woodward arrived 

Louise Woodward arrives home 
BULLETIN 

Louise Woodward faces battle to rebuild life after conviction 

diplomatic compound 

Bizarre denouement in conflict over ambassadors' homes in Belarus 
Belarus' president claims ownership of ambassadors' residence 

mario stanic put 
shin bet chief ami ayalon recently withdrew 
late dictator gen 
tunisia chokri el ouaer 
nba players 
west bank 
tunisians tossed bottles 

Ld−Writethru,0813 

World Cup: Some of the delinquents were goaded into action 

crowd booed pioline 

EDS: retransmits with tennis in slug 
French player kicked out for verbal abuse 

strongman hun sen 

Political killings condemned; opposition party to defy ban 
Prince's party condemns killing of party workers 

germany's chancellor kohl 

German opposition leader holds Polish talks 

airline suffered 4.2 billion yen 

Two airline unions call off strikes; third to walk off as planned 

tear gas 
jordan 
game 6 
dlrs 50 million 
national team 
butler 
foreign ministry 

5.2 seconds left 

world cup game 

Nearly 15,000 tickets stolen; state phone company probing fraud 
World Cup: Norway unbeaten in 16 games but disappointed 

kosovo 
security council 
japanese yen 

Dollar edges higher, stocks fall 
Precede LONDON 
China welcomes efforts to strengthen Japanese yen 
Asian rallies fail to impress European markets 

itar−tass news agency 

eu 
south korea's 

Two Koreas may jointly celebrate liberation day in August 
World Cup: Mexico prepares for Belgium, attacks reporters 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10" validated="false" coords="8,116.75,240.78,352.50,185.69"><figDesc coords="8,345.40,415.45,7.86,11.02;8,349.88,404.07,3.38,11.28;8,349.88,391.67,3.38,11.60;8,349.88,385.72,3.38,5.15;8,349.88,375.73,3.38,9.18;8,349.88,366.87,3.38,8.05;8,349.88,362.84,3.38,3.22;8,349.88,357.37,3.38,4.67;8,349.88,349.95,3.38,6.61;8,349.88,341.74,3.38,7.41">yassin Report: Egyptian embassy tells Hamas leader he can enter Egypt</figDesc><table coords="8,116.75,240.78,352.50,185.69">dlrs 50 million 
south africa 

World Cup: Denmark and South Africa draw 1−1 in ''strange match'' 

late dictator gen 
tunisia chokri el ouaer 
diplomatic compound 
interfax news agency quoted chubais 

Chubais calls for dlrs 10 billion to 15 billion in aid to Russia 
BC−Russia−Economy, 1st Ld 

tear gas 
tunisians tossed bottles 
crowd booed pioline 
germany's chancellor kohl 
strongman hun sen 

airline suffered 4.2 billion yen 
national team 
premier sergei kiriyenko's cabinet 

Communists denounce re−appointment of Chubais 

financial crisis 

12 players 
increasingly popular gambling vehicle 

foreign ministry 

world cup game 

World Cup violent play worries Brazil 
World Cup: Nigeria into second round with 1−0 victory 
World Cup: U.S. players happy at attention; Iran going for victory 
Already qualified, Brazil still has revenge for motivation 
World Cup: Japan seeks life−saving upset against Croatia 

kosovo 

Kosovo leader calls for NATO help, admits no control over KLA 
World Cup: Troubled Yugoslavs look for joy with win against 
Yugoslav minister commits to dialogue; Says Belgrade wants to join 

eu 
english fans 
japanese yen 

World finance officials meet to discuss Asian financial crisis 
Trading in Long Term Credit Bank suspended after downgrade 

interfax news agency 
south korea 

World Cup: Bergkamp back, Kluivert out as Dutch take on South 

detroit red wings 
netanyahu adviser david bar−illan 

Newspaper mock referendum: two−thirds favor West Bank withdrawal 

</table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11" validated="false" coords="8,116.75,50.01,355.68,703.15"><figDesc coords="8,121.23,125.07,3.38,14.33;8,121.23,116.85,3.38,7.41;8,121.23,104.13,3.38,11.92;8,121.23,92.05,3.38,11.27;8,121.23,85.93,3.38,5.32;8,125.11,131.84,3.38,7.57;8,125.11,124.91,3.38,6.12;8,125.11,119.11,3.38,4.99;8,125.11,108.80,3.38,9.51;8,125.11,99.62,3.38,8.38;8,125.11,90.60,3.38,8.22;8,125.11,84.87,3.38,4.92;8,129.00,131.84,3.38,7.57;8,129.00,124.91,3.38,6.12;8,129.00,112.19,3.38,11.92;8,129.00,104.14,3.38,7.25;8,129.00,98.41,3.38,4.92;8,129.00,91.33,3.38,6.28;8,129.00,85.37,3.38,5.15;8,129.00,79.89,3.38,4.67;8,129.00,65.88,3.38,13.21;8,132.89,131.84,3.38,7.57;8,132.89,124.91,3.38,6.12;8,132.89,118.79,3.38,5.32;8,132.89,112.35,3.38,5.64;8,132.89,108.48,3.38,3.06;8,132.89,101.23,3.38,6.45;8,132.89,92.69,3.38,7.73;8,136.78,131.84,3.38,7.57;8,136.78,124.91,3.38,6.12;8,136.78,116.70,3.38,7.41;8,136.78,107.35,3.38,8.54;8,136.78,97.20,3.38,9.34;8,136.78,90.44,3.38,5.95;8,136.78,80.46,3.38,9.18;8,136.78,68.54,3.38,11.11;8,136.78,60.00,3.38,7.73;8,148.20,127.90,3.69,12.32;8,148.20,110.18,3.69,16.64;8,152.68,129.10,3.38,10.31;8,152.68,124.91,3.38,3.38;8,152.68,114.44,3.38,9.67;8,152.68,106.38,3.38,7.25;8,152.68,98.33,3.38,7.25;8,152.68,88.18,3.38,9.34;8,152.68,81.58,3.38,5.80;8,152.68,77.39,3.38,3.38;8,152.68,68.69,3.38,7.90;8,164.45,130.70,3.69,9.51;8,164.45,117.09,3.69,12.53;8,168.94,132.32,3.38,7.09;8,168.94,123.78,3.38,7.73;8,168.94,108.80,3.38,14.18;8,168.94,100.42,3.38,7.57;8,168.94,91.88,3.38,7.73;8,168.94,85.44,3.38,5.64;8,168.94,66.26,3.38,18.37;8,168.94,60.30,3.38,5.15;8,168.94,50.48,3.38,9.02;8,176.82,130.92,3.69,9.29;8,176.82,120.77,3.69,9.07;8,176.82,102.83,3.69,16.86;8,181.31,131.84,3.38,7.57;8,181.31,124.11,3.38,6.92;8,181.31,115.41,3.38,7.89;8,181.31,107.84,3.38,6.76;8,181.31,99.31,3.38,7.73;8,181.31,92.06,3.38,6.45;8,181.31,83.20,3.38,8.05;8,181.31,80.14,3.38,2.25;8,181.31,68.86,3.38,10.47;8,181.31,59.20,3.38,8.86;8,188.49,127.46,3.69,12.75;8,188.49,117.31,3.69,9.07;8,188.49,103.70,3.69,12.53;8,196.61,124.22,3.69,15.99;8,196.61,115.79,3.69,7.35;8,196.61,99.15,3.69,15.56;8,196.61,88.79,3.69,9.29;8,201.10,125.07,3.38,14.34;8,201.10,119.59,3.38,4.67;8,201.10,110.09,3.38,8.70;8,201.10,99.13,3.38,10.15;8,201.10,93.01,3.38,5.32;8,201.10,84.64,3.38,7.57;8,201.10,79.16,3.38,4.67;8,201.10,70.14,3.38,8.22;8,204.98,119.67,3.38,19.73;8,204.98,108.56,3.38,10.31;8,204.98,97.28,3.38,10.47;8,204.98,84.72,3.38,11.76;8,204.98,75.70,3.38,8.22;8,204.98,68.93,3.38,5.96;8,211.81,133.08,3.69,7.13;8,211.81,122.06,3.69,9.94;8,216.29,130.22,3.38,9.18;8,216.29,123.62,3.38,5.80;8,216.29,110.41,3.38,12.40;8,216.29,101.71,3.38,7.89;8,216.29,93.82,3.38,7.09;8,220.18,122.49,3.38,16.91;8,220.18,115.57,3.38,6.12;8,220.18,105.42,3.38,9.34;8,220.18,93.98,3.38,10.63;8,220.18,87.70,3.38,5.48;8,224.07,130.39,3.38,9.02;8,224.07,120.40,3.38,9.18;8,224.07,117.18,3.38,2.42;8,224.07,113.15,3.38,3.22;8,224.07,103.81,3.38,8.53;8,224.07,90.12,3.38,12.89;8,224.07,82.22,3.38,7.09;8,229.83,135.03,3.69,5.18;8,229.83,116.23,3.69,17.72;8,234.32,130.87,3.38,8.54;8,234.32,116.21,3.38,13.85;8,234.32,106.39,3.38,9.02;8,234.32,94.14,3.38,11.44;8,234.32,87.06,3.38,6.28;8,234.32,71.43,3.38,14.82;8,234.32,67.25,3.38,3.38;8,234.32,58.07,3.38,8.38;8,234.32,50.01,3.38,7.25;8,240.79,130.92,3.69,9.29;8,240.79,120.99,3.69,8.85;8,248.21,128.76,3.69,11.45;8,248.21,119.04,3.69,8.64;8,255.63,130.27,3.69,9.94;8,255.63,111.05,3.69,18.15;8,260.11,131.19,3.38,8.21;8,260.11,118.63,3.38,11.75;8,260.11,113.48,3.38,4.35;8,260.11,100.43,3.38,12.24;8,260.11,94.63,3.38,4.99;8,260.11,86.57,3.38,7.25;8,260.11,75.14,3.38,10.63;8,260.11,68.37,3.38,5.96;8,260.11,59.51,3.38,8.06;8,266.23,128.54,3.69,11.67;8,266.23,120.12,3.69,7.35;8,270.72,135.54,3.38,3.87;8,270.72,125.71,3.38,9.02;8,270.72,103.24,3.38,21.67;8,274.60,131.84,3.38,7.57;8,274.60,124.91,3.38,6.12;8,274.60,119.11,3.38,4.99;8,274.60,112.51,3.38,5.80;8,274.60,102.04,3.38,9.66;8,274.60,93.99,3.38,7.25;8,274.60,88.27,3.38,4.92;8,280.02,116.88,3.69,23.33;8,286.38,131.35,7.86,8.86;8,290.86,122.17,3.38,8.38;8,290.86,115.73,3.38,5.64;8,290.86,107.84,3.38,7.09;8,290.86,101.88,3.38,5.15;8,290.86,87.05,3.38,14.02;8,296.27,127.68,7.86,12.53;8,300.76,123.46,3.38,5.80;8,300.76,117.02,3.38,5.64;8,300.76,109.12,3.38,7.09;8,306.17,127.46,3.69,12.75;8,306.17,117.31,3.69,9.07;8,306.17,103.70,3.69,12.53;8,306.17,90.73,3.69,11.89;8,306.17,76.25,3.69,13.40;8,312.53,127.68,3.69,12.53;8,312.53,119.47,3.69,7.13;8,312.53,101.43,3.69,16.96;8,318.54,130.70,3.69,9.51;8,318.54,120.12,3.69,9.50;8,323.02,128.61,3.38,10.79;8,323.02,121.85,3.38,5.96;8,323.02,113.47,3.38,7.57;8,323.02,108.96,3.38,3.70;8,323.02,97.37,3.38,10.79;8,323.02,86.90,3.38,9.67;8,323.02,80.62,3.38,5.47;8,323.02,64.83,3.38,14.98;8,323.02,58.39,3.38,5.64;8,328.08,132.87,3.69,7.34;8,328.08,124.44,3.69,7.35;8,334.09,127.68,3.69,12.53;8,340.10,133.73,3.69,6.48;8,340.10,123.58,3.69,9.07;8,344.58,131.83,3.38,7.57;8,344.58,122.33,3.38,8.70;8,344.58,118.47,3.38,3.06;8,344.58,99.14,3.38,18.52;8,344.58,91.57,3.38,6.76;8,344.58,85.61,3.38,5.15;8,344.58,77.23,3.38,7.57;8,344.58,74.17,3.38,2.25;8,344.58,64.19,3.38,9.18;8,349.28,124.65,3.69,15.56;8,349.28,114.07,3.69,9.50;8,349.28,109.10,3.69,3.89;8,349.28,95.28,3.69,12.75;8,353.77,134.41,3.38,4.99;8,353.77,124.26,3.38,9.34;8,353.77,110.57,3.38,12.89;8,353.77,106.39,3.38,3.38;8,353.77,101.55,3.38,4.03;8,353.77,93.50,3.38,7.24;8,353.77,90.28,3.38,2.42;8,353.77,81.58,3.38,7.89;8,353.77,71.91,3.38,8.86;8,353.77,64.35,3.38,6.76;8,358.47,123.46,3.69,16.75;8,358.47,112.45,3.69,9.94;8,358.47,102.07,3.69,9.29;8,364.13,126.38,3.69,13.83;8,364.13,113.42,3.69,11.88;8,364.13,101.97,3.69,10.37;8,364.13,88.35,3.69,12.53;8,368.61,131.84,3.38,7.57;8,368.61,124.91,3.38,6.12;8,368.61,115.09,3.38,9.02;8,368.61,101.07,3.38,13.21;8,368.61,98.01,3.38,2.25;8,368.61,90.12,3.38,7.09;8,368.61,83.52,3.38,5.80;8,368.61,75.62,3.38,7.09;8,368.61,67.89,3.38,6.93;8,368.61,56.13,3.38,10.96;8,372.50,130.39,3.38,9.02;8,372.50,116.37,3.38,13.21;8,372.50,113.31,3.38,2.25;8,372.50,105.42,3.38,7.09;8,372.50,98.82,3.38,5.80;8,372.50,90.92,3.38,7.09;8,372.50,83.19,3.38,6.93;8,372.50,71.91,3.38,10.47;8,372.50,60.15,3.38,10.96;8,376.85,125.52,3.69,14.69;8,376.85,113.85,3.69,10.59;8,376.85,98.94,3.69,13.83;8,381.33,136.67,3.38,2.74;8,381.33,129.74,3.38,6.12;8,381.33,124.42,3.38,4.51;8,381.33,117.17,3.38,6.45;8,381.33,113.31,3.38,3.06;8,381.33,106.06,3.38,6.44;8,381.33,98.01,3.38,7.24;8,381.33,92.69,3.38,4.51;8,381.33,81.26,3.38,10.63;8,386.04,128.54,3.69,11.67;8,386.04,113.42,3.69,14.04;8,386.04,96.35,3.69,15.99;8,386.04,79.72,3.69,15.55;8,386.04,62.66,3.69,15.98;8,390.52,133.77,3.38,5.64;8,390.52,124.75,3.38,8.21;8,390.52,115.25,3.38,8.69;8,390.52,112.19,3.38,2.25;8,390.52,101.88,3.38,9.50;8,390.52,97.69,3.38,3.38;8,390.52,90.93,3.38,5.96;8,390.52,86.90,3.38,3.22;8,390.52,71.91,3.38,14.18;8,390.52,59.35,3.38,11.76;8,395.23,128.54,3.69,11.67;8,395.23,110.61,3.69,16.85;8,395.23,93.11,3.69,16.42;8,395.23,77.12,3.69,14.91;8,399.71,129.42,3.38,9.99;8,399.71,116.69,3.38,11.92;8,399.71,110.41,3.38,5.48;8,399.71,107.18,3.38,2.42;8,399.71,97.68,3.38,8.70;8,399.71,83.51,3.38,13.37;8,399.71,71.59,3.38,11.11;8,399.71,68.36,3.38,2.42;8,399.71,52.74,3.38,14.82;8,403.60,131.99,3.38,7.41;8,403.60,120.08,3.38,11.11;8,403.60,110.10,3.38,9.18;8,403.60,98.66,3.38,10.63;8,403.60,95.44,3.38,2.42;8,403.60,85.93,3.38,8.70;8,403.60,71.76,3.38,13.37;8,407.95,130.70,3.69,9.51;8,407.95,115.79,3.69,13.83;8,413.60,128.77,7.86,11.44;8,418.09,120.72,3.38,7.25;8,418.09,112.67,3.38,7.25;8,418.09,107.19,3.38,4.67;8,418.09,98.65,3.38,7.73;8,418.09,89.48,3.38,8.37;8,455.55,132.32,3.38,7.09;8,455.55,126.04,3.38,5.47;8,455.55,122.01,3.38,3.22;8,455.55,118.79,3.38,2.42;8,455.55,109.13,3.38,8.86;8,455.55,105.90,3.38,2.42;8,455.55,98.17,3.38,6.93;8,455.55,93.98,3.38,3.38;8,455.55,86.41,3.38,6.76;8,455.55,83.19,3.38,2.42;8,455.55,70.14,3.38,12.24;8,459.90,130.92,3.69,9.29;8,459.90,122.28,3.69,7.56;8,459.90,106.72,3.69,14.47;8,459.90,95.49,3.69,10.15;8,464.38,133.61,3.38,5.80;8,464.38,125.07,3.38,7.73;8,464.38,122.01,3.38,2.25;8,464.38,109.60,3.38,11.60;8,464.38,106.38,3.38,2.42;8,464.38,95.91,3.38,9.66;8,464.38,79.80,3.38,15.31;8,464.38,59.34,3.38,19.65;8,468.73,130.92,3.69,9.29;8,468.73,114.94,3.69,14.90;8,468.73,100.03,3.69,13.82;8,267.84,745.03,76.00,8.12">Sampson's future uncertain following Cup World Cup: Iran defeats United States 2−1 World Cup: Germany grabs 2−2 draw with late comeback World Cup: Cha fired as head coach World Cup: Saudi coach, players miss sacked Brazilian coach kosovo albanians Fighting for Kosovo roads rages despite calls for peace south korea's North Korea denounces South Korea over Independence Day festival tokyo stock exchange Dollar rises, Tokyo stock prices edge higher in morning trading interfax news agency president joao bernardo vieira Thousands flee Bissau fighting, only trickle find refuge Guinea−Bissau loyalists demand ceasefire before talks final round Barnes wins Canadian senior event Montgomerie can't escape heckling fans Woods looking to be 'major' contender again ms woodward Louise Woodward implies Eappens were responsible for baby's death asian crisis soccer team social democrats Czech socialists win elections, fear tough coalition talks ahead iranian fans AP Photos XWCLY103−107 World Cup: Iran wins political game 2−1 ambassadors cart Martin leaves U.S. Open with confidence stewart Janzen wins U.S. Open interfax news agency quoted chubais korea's choi yong−soo south africa Spencer says Diana TV program drained him; controversy over time shot players 150 riyals Three injured as demonstrators clash with police in Yemen ayatollah mirza ali gharavi Iraq blames foreigners for the killing of senior Iranian cleric blue−chip nikkei index regional prefect daniel cadoux World Cup: French policeman in coma after being hit by hooligan French policeman in coma after being hit by German hooligan sporadic power outages At least five dead as freak storm hits Moscow deputy treasury secretary lawrence summers U.S. official arrives in Jakarta for talks on Indonesian economy extend jerusalem municipal authority Cabinet approves plan to extend Jerusalem authority to settlements Egypt criticizes Israel's decision to extend Jerusalem south koreans holes Giggling golfer earns first LPGA victory Iraq's Aziz off to Madrid to lobby for lifting of sanctions world food program wants U.N. envoy in Baghdad to discuss oil−for−food implementation world currency markets Figure 4: 06/21/1998</figDesc><table coords="8,116.75,68.36,338.01,262.69">shells rain down on Guinea−Bissau capital 

dlrs 50 million 
usa basketball 
west bank 
yassin 
blue−chip nikkei index 
germany's chancellor kohl 

Germany begins reluctant farewell to D−mark after 50 years 

ernie els 
tear gas 
world's financial markets 

U.S. looking for more from China in proposal for WTO membership 

tunisians tossed bottles 
crowd booed pioline 
financial times−stock exchange 100−share index 
strongman hun sen 

airline suffered 4.2 billion yen 
increasingly popular gambling vehicle 
international financial organizations 

kosovo albanians 

Four Serbian policemen held by militants, fighting goes on 
Four Serbian policemen held by militants 

iran 

Tight security in place for Iran−U.S. match 
Iran says one of its senior cleric has been killed in Iraq 
World Cup: Much more than a game: Politics, second round at stake 
Soccer brings together Iranians from all sides of the political 

english fans 

No incidents reported in Toulouse as English fans trickle in 

asian crisis 

Hollway plays down dollar drop 

south korea 
interfax news agency 

Kidnappers of Russian envoy make ransom demand 

ms woodward 

Louise Woodward has 'lots of answers,' mother says 

oust president joao bernardo vieira 

Post−colonial Guinea−bissau plunges into darkness 

Rebels hold airport, gunfire rattles through Bissau 

japanese yen 

prime minister benjamin netanyahu 
world cup finals 

Saudi Arabia fires Brazilian coach Parreira 

social democrats 

Czech socialists win elections, fear tough coalition talks ahead 
Initial results show socialists ahead in Czech elections 
Exit polls have socalists leading in Czech early elections 

korea's choi yong−soo 

World Cup: Classy Dutch rout South Korea 5−0 
World Cup: Dutch win 5−0 to eliminate Koreans 
World Cup: Cocu, Overmars give Dutch 2−0 halftime lead 

ambassadors 

European Union ambassadors to leave Belarus 

interfax news agency quoted chubais 
players 

With Sports−Soccer−Germany−Yugoslavia 

keeper edwin van der sar 
strongman hun sen 

Other nations urge Cambodian parties not to boycott election 

nation party 

One Nation makes Asian Australians feel ''unwelcome:'' Howard 

time shot 
south african captain lucas radebe 
cart 
stewart 
yassin 
soccer game 
100 pro−islamic students began saturday 

Turkish students march to protest head scarf ban 
Turkish students launch march head scarf ban 

blue−chip nikkei index 

tear gas 

Police fire in air as protests in Yemen continue 

sports fans 
tunisians tossed bottles 
crowd booed pioline 
financial times−stock exchange 100−share index 
ernie els 
world currency markets 

World financial officials urge Japan to revive economy 

deputy treasury secretary lawrence summers 
footed shot home 
regional prefect jean−paul proust relented 

world cup 

100 pro−islamic students began saturday 
john jairo toro 
nation party 
fans 
regional prefect jean−paul proust relented 
asian nations 

</table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </head><p> This work was supported by the National Visualization and Analytics Center (NVAC), a U.S. Department of Homeland Security Program operated by the Pacific Northwest National Laboratory. </p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct coords="6,336.24,601.00,114.43,7.22"  xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">CERATOPS. MPQA Corpus</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="6,336.24,610.36,221.82,7.22;6,336.24,619.84,221.70,7.22;6,336.24,629.32,181.27,7.22"  xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The tdt-2 text and speech corpus</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<forename type="middle">C</forename>
				<surname>David</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">D</forename>
				<surname>Graff</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Liberman</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">N</forename>
				<surname>Martey</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">S</forename>
				<surname>Strassel</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Proceedings of DARPA Broadcast News Workshop</title>
		<meeting>DARPA Broadcast News Workshop</meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Morgan Kaufmann</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="60" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="6,336.24,638.80,221.66,7.22;6,336.24,648.28,221.65,7.22;6,336.24,657.76,221.62,7.22;6,336.24,667.24,142.27,7.22"  xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Visualizing tags over time</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">M</forename>
				<surname>Dubinko</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">R</forename>
				<surname>Kumar</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Magnani</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">J</forename>
				<surname>Novak</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">P</forename>
				<surname>Raghavan</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">A</forename>
				<surname>Tomkins</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">WWW &apos;06: Proceedings of the 15th international conference on World Wide Web</title>
		<meeting><address><addrLine>New York, NY, USA</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>ACM</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
			<biblScope unit="page" from="193" to="202" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="6,336.24,676.72,221.59,7.22;6,336.24,686.08,221.53,7.22;6,336.24,695.56,143.59,7.22"  xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improving browsing in digital libraries with keyphrase indexes</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Gutwin</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">G</forename>
				<surname>Paynter</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">I</forename>
				<surname>Witten</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">C</forename>
				<surname>Nevill-Manning</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Frank</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Decision Support Systems</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="81" to="104" />
			<date type="published" when="1999" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct coords="6,336.24,705.04,221.59,7.22;6,336.24,714.52,158.47,7.22"  xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Lucene in action. Action series</title>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">E</forename>
				<surname>Hatcher</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName>
				<forename type="first">O</forename>
				<surname>Gospodnetic</surname>
			</persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
			<publisher>Manning Publications Co</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Greenwich, CT</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
